<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The study of quietness explained, recommended, and directed in a sermon preached before the Right Honourable the Lord Mayor and Court of Aldermen, at the Guild-Hall chappel, March 16, 1683/4, and now published, as the heads were, elsewhere, more enlarged upon, in several discourses.</title>
            <author>Pearson, Richard, d. 1734.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1684</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 119 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 35 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A53909</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P1017</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R6934</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12588009</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12588009</idno>
            <idno type="VID">63795</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A53909)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 63795)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 674:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The study of quietness explained, recommended, and directed in a sermon preached before the Right Honourable the Lord Mayor and Court of Aldermen, at the Guild-Hall chappel, March 16, 1683/4, and now published, as the heads were, elsewhere, more enlarged upon, in several discourses.</title>
                  <author>Pearson, Richard, d. 1734.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[7], 59, [4] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by R.H. for H. Bonwicke ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1684.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Richard Pearson. Cf. NUC pre-1956.</note>
                  <note>Advertisement: p. [2]-[4] at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Quietude --  Sermons.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="order">
            <pb facs="tcp:63795:1"/>
            <head>Tulce Major.</head>
            <opener>
               <date>Martis <hi>XVIII.</hi> Die Martii, 1683/4. Anno<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Regni Regis <hi>CAROLI</hi> Secundi <hi>Angliae,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>XXXVI.</hi>
               </date>
            </opener>
            <p>THIS Court doth deſire Mr. <hi>Pearſon</hi> to Print his Sermon, Preached at the <hi>Guild-Hall</hi> Chappel, on <hi>Sunday</hi> laſt before the Lord Major and Court of Aldermen of this City.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Wagſtaffe.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:63795:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE STUDY OF QUIETNESS Explained, Recommended, and Directed, IN A SERMON Preached before The Right Honourable the LORD MAYOR and Court of Aldermen, At the <hi>G<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ILD-HALL CHAPPEL, March</hi> 16. 1683/4.</p>
            <p>And now Publiſhed, as the Heads were, elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where, more Enlarged upon, in ſeveral Diſcourſes.</p>
            <p>By <hi>RICHARD PEARSON</hi> Rector of St. <hi>Michael</hi>'s <hi>Crooked-Lane, LONDON.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>P. H.</hi> for <hi>Henry Bonwicke</hi> at the <hi>Red-Lyon</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-Yard, 1684.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:63795:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:63795:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Honourable, Sir HENRY TUICE, Lord Mayor of the City of <hi>London.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IN Obedience to your Lordſhip's Order, I have now made this plain Diſcourſe publick. That which I beforehand most aſſuredly expected, has ſince accordingly befallen me, upon my Preaching of this Sermon; which hath brought me under the gentle Diſcipline of the long-ago-erected Phanatick-Office<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that is, (if there can be any need to explain my meaning) I have been bitterly Curſed and Railed at, and both my Self and my Diſcourſe vilely aſperſed, with an hundred Lies and Slanders, and moſt ridiculous and malicious Miſrepreſentations. And, indeed, ſince I must needs be venturing to tell theſe Men their own (though out of never ſo charitable a Deſign) how could I expect to eſcape that, which has been the never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>failing
<pb facs="tcp:63795:3"/>
Portion of all others, who have yet done the like? or think to come off, without having <hi>a Caſt of their Office?</hi> Nor have I now therefore the leaſt reaſon, to take it ill that I ſhould be thus treated by them, according to the conſtant Methods of their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Trade and Myſtery. <hi>For, to Rail and Slan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> is the only way, which this ſort of Men yet ever knew, of requiting thoſe Perſons, who ſpeak to them Home-truths, and give them ſober Counſels. This is their only ſignificant and most ſubstantial way of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation, in theſe Caſes. And under this Notion, I can aſſure them, I have now learn'd to take all their preſent Treatment; which I do therefore not only readily forgive; but, over and above, return them hearty thanks for the ſame; profeſsing withal, that I will ſtill carefully endeavour (according to their Rules of judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing) never to deſerve leſs, from their hands. If <hi>their</hi> Deſign, herein, has been quite contrary, and they far enough from having any Intention to gratifie me, I cannot tell how to help their being defeated; they muſt e'en beſtow their Lies elſewhere, for the future. For for my part in theſe Caſes, I ſhall ever look upon ſuch courſe Complements as the greateſt Credit and
<pb facs="tcp:63795:3"/>
Courteſies, that theſe Men are capable of doing me, till I ſee they come once to have a more real Kindneſs for their own Souls. In the mean time, in point of Gratitude for what I have already received, I think my ſelf obliged to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint them, with this ſecret, <hi>viz.</hi> That, if they have indeed a mind most effectually to ſhame, vex and diſoblige me, their only way will be, <hi>to ſpeak well of me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As to the Diſcourſe itſelf, I ſhall only ſay thus much; that though there are now ſeveral things added, and more enlarged upon, yet there is nothing at all omitted of what was delivered before your Lordſhip. And I must now leave it to all impartial Readers, to judge, whether in the whole, there be any thing (of my own) either ſo prophane or ridiculous, as that any one, who is not himſelf troubled with over moiſt a Brain, ſhall need (as ſome very gravely pretend they did, at the hearing of it) <hi>to ſweat for me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>My Lord, I have no more to add, but that no man ſhall more heartily Pray, for your Lordſhips Happineſs
<pb facs="tcp:63795:4"/>
and Proſperity, for the ſucceſsfull Government, Peace, and true Welfare of this City, than</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Lordſhips moſt Humble and Obedient Servant
R. Pearſon.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:63795:4"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>1 THES. 4. 11.</bibl>
               <q>And that ye ſtudy to be quiet, and to do your own Buſineſs, &amp;c.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THough Peace and Quietneſs be a thing in it ſelf ſo highly deſirable, and eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentially conducive to the preſent temporal, as well as the future eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Happineſs of men; and though Strife and Diſcord be conſtantly at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended with ſuch Miſery and Confuſion, that any to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerably wiſe man cannot but ſtand amazed at the prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Folly and Madneſs of thoſe who make it ſo their only<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Buſineſs to diſquiet the World, and themſelves; yet (which is worſt of all) no Perſons are ever more hardly perſwaded to conſider what they do, to be made ſenſible of their folly, or willing to admit of any proper Remedy for their Diſeaſe, than ſuch turbulent factious Spirits. Who, whilſt in the heat of their Paſſion and Diſorder, are commonly ſo far from hearing any Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Reaſon or Religion, which would tend to pacifie and bring them to a better Mind, that the very Propoſal of any ſuch Arguments does uſually but ſo much the more exaſperate and enrage them, and make them become extreamly furious alſo againſt him, who does but offer to make any ſuch charitable Applications to them.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:63795:5"/>Thus popular Tumult and Faction is apt at firſt, like a violent Torrent, to carry all before it. And ſuch men, whilſt in their full Carreer, are as deaf to all moral Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments, as the very Bruits; till at laſt, when either they have wearied out themſelves, or come to be over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>powred by Authority, and forcibly reſtrained from proceeding, or are made a little to ſmart for, and feel the bad Effects of their own Diſorders; then, perhaps they may become more docible, and ready to hear ſuch ſound reaſon, as may prevail upon them, for the future, to betake themſelves to more regular Courſes, and a peaceable Behaviour.</p>
            <p>And now, as this Obſervation hath generally proved true, as to the men of moſt other Ages and Places of the World, and as the firſt part of it has been already too ſadly and notoriouſly fulfilled, by very many men of our own Time and Nation; ſo 'tis to be hoped, that now the ſecond part of it will alſo be no leſs verified, in the future Temper and Behaviour of the ſame Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons.</p>
            <p>'Tis but a very little while ago (if it be indeed yet over) ſince very conſiderable numbers amongſt us, were, by the wicked Artifices of ſome of the worſt of men, boil'd up into ſuch a height of Tumult and Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, ſo wholly bent upon Faction, Diſorder, and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion, that no ſober Counſels or Perſwaſions of thoſe who ſincerely endeavoured to maintain Peace could find any tolerable Reception. Men were grown far wiſer than all their regular Teachers; and only admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and betook themſelves to ſuch falſe Guides, as would firſt ſuffer themſelves to be guided and inſtructed, by their fond Diſciples, how, and what to teach them; ſuch only as would be ſure ſtill to infuſe into them more and more unreſonable Fears and Jealouſies; make
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:63795:5"/>
them more froward, diſcontented, and ſeditious, and fire them on into an open Combuſtion.</p>
            <p>As for thoſe faithful Monitors (as, God be praiſed, there were many) who, according to their bounden Duty, continued to preach to the People, <hi>Truſt in God, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liance upon the divine Providence,</hi> who ſincerely inculca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to them, <hi>the conſtant Doctrine and Example of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles and Primitive Chriſtians;</hi> ſuch men failed not to be mortally hated, ſcoffed at, and publickly derided, for their pains, by many, who were not aſhamed to give out, by way of anſwer to all this; <hi>That we of this Age are but little concerned in what the Apoſtles either ſaid, or did; and that, had they lived in our Circumſtances, they would have preached and acted quite contrary to what they did;</hi> many times withal, not obſcurely in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinuating as if they thought their own Teachers, now in this Age of Light, far better acquainted with the true Chriſtian Liberty, in theſe Particulars, than the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry firſt inſpired Planters of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>In ſhort, for one to have taken ſuch a Text as this but two years ago, and ſolidly and pertinently to have diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſed upon it, according to the true meaning and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign thereof, was enough, without any more ado, to call a man's <hi>true Proteſtantſhip</hi> in queſtion, and to make him ſhrewdly ſuſpected for, and to give him the black Character of (that under which they comprehend all evil) <hi>a Perſon Popiſhly affected.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But now at length, ſince by a wonderful Providence, the helliſh Deſigns of the accurſed Promoters of our Diſcord, and wicked Ring-leaders of the Faction have been ſo clearly diſcovered and defeated; ſince ſo good Proviſion alſo is made, by the watchful Endeavours of a Wiſe and Gracious Prince, that it may be no more in the power of ſuch men, by the ſame Methods to diſturb the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:63795:6"/>
Publick Peace, or to bring Ruine and Confuſion upon themſelves, and others; ſince ſome of them have like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe taſted the bitter Fruits of their former Diſorders and wicked Follies; I hope now, that all men will ſo far open their eyes and ears, as not to be any more ſo inra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged againſt faithful Admonitions, nor to think a Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of this Nature unſeaſonable.</p>
            <p>Now men are come a little more to themſelves again, and grown cooler, I hope that of the Preacher may be verified in them, Eccleſ. 9. 17. <hi>And the words of wiſe men will now be heard in quiet, more than the cry of him that ruled among Fools,</hi> that is (as the learned <hi>Grotius</hi> paraphraſeth it) rather than the Clamours of a factious Tribune of the People, or the Suggeſtions of any ſedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Demagogue of the ſilly Vulgar.</p>
            <p>Now ſuch men will be more at leiſure to ſit down a little, and ſoberly conſider, <hi>what it is they have gained,</hi> by their former Unquietneſs, Cabals, Riots, Tumults, and unnatural Conſpiracies; and may, perhaps, be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented hereafter, to give St. <hi>Paul</hi> a patient hearing, and look upon it worth their while alſo to think at length, of practiſing his excellently Political no leſs than Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Advice, whilſt he, here in my Text, moſt earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beſeecheth them, <hi>That they would ſtudy to be quiet, and to do their own Buſineſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which though it be to be looked upon as a complica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Exhortation, and there are two diſtinct things which we are here preſs'd to; ſo that I might, and ſhall alſo (ſo far as it may be thought neceſſary) handle them diſtinctly: yet ſince the ſecond is here recommended only for the ſake of the firſt, and we are called upon to mind our own Affairs, and to do our own Buſineſs, and keep our ſelves within the compaſs of our own proper Callings, as one excellent means, in order to the procuring and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:63795:6"/>
maintaining that Peace and Quiet, for which mainly we are to ſtudy; I ſhall therefore content my ſelf with en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavouring theſe three General Things.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>First,</hi> To ſhew, <hi>What it is to be quiet,</hi> or who they are that may be truly ſaid, <hi>to ſtudy to be quiet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> To conſider, and briefly to demonſtrate what abſolute neceſſity there is of the moſt earneſt ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and contrivance, of the moſt diligent care and cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſpection to be uſed by all thoſe who would lead a quiet and a peaceable life.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> I ſhall endeavour to ſhew how this ſtudy of ours may be beſt directed; or, in what Particulars chiefly our care to this purpoſe may moſt ſuccesflully be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed.</p>
            <p>And then, in the laſt place, I ſhall conclude the whole with ſome ſeaſonable Application.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> I am to ſhew, what it is to be quiet, or who they are that may be truly ſaid, <hi>to ſtudy to be quiet.</hi> Nor will this Enquiry (as ſome may be apt to think it) be altogether unneceſſary or impertinent: Since though it may ſeem eaſily enough to be underſtood, yet (like ſeveral other plain things) it may be liable to be miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken. And, I fear, there are but too many who are no leſs Strangers to the full meaning and true notion of the thing, than they are to the practice of the Duty it ſelf; as perhaps, 'twill better appear in my farther Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication.</p>
            <p>Now <hi>Quietneſs</hi> here may be taken both <hi>Paſſively</hi> and <hi>Actively;</hi> and he is truly quiet, who is neither himſelf
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:63795:7"/>
reſtleſs and diſturbed in his own mind, nor yet any ways diſturbs others that are about him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>First,</hi> To be quiet (in that which I call the paſſive ſenſe) is no other than to be of a calm, even, well com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed Temper; to have a man's mind at reſt and eaſe, void of all Sowerneſs, Diſcontent, Peeviſhneſs, ſecret Murmurings and Repinings at God's Providential Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſations; not apt to be ruffled or diſordered, by any troubleſome and inordinate Luſts and Paſſions, but full of <hi>Love, Joy, Peace;</hi> well contented with that ſtate and circumſtances of condition, which Providence has at preſent allotted the man; and far from deſiring any violent or irregular alteration.</p>
            <p>And now this inward Peace and Tranquility<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> of Mind is indeed the only true Foundation of all other Quietneſs. Which, in the Second Acceptation, is no other than a peaceable Temper and Behaviour towards other men. In which active ſenſe of the Word (here mainly deſigned in my Text<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>) that man only can be truly ſaid to ſtudy to be quiet, who has ſuch a ſpecial care over himſelf, over all his <hi>Deeds, Words,</hi> and <hi>Thoughts,</hi> as never wittingly to Do, Say, or Deſign, nor yet to countenance, or any way encourage any other in the doing, ſaying, or deſigning any thing that is apt to cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate Hatred, Faction, or Diſcord, in the Church or State; or may tend to the Injury, or Diſturbance of that Kingdom, City, Society or Family, of which he is a Member; but, on the contrary, endeavours, in all Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars, both ſo to demean himſelf, and (as much as in him lies) to prevail with all others alſo after ſuch a manner to behave themſelves, as may beſt comport with the Peace of man-kind in general, and tend to the Benefit and Eſtabliſhment of that Lawful Government
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:63795:7"/>
in particular, under which he is a Subject. But ſtill, in order to the Rectifying or Prevention of ſeveral too common Miſtakes, it may not, perhaps, be inconvenient for me ſomewhat more particularly and diſtinctly to inſiſt upon, and explain the ſeveral Parts of this gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Deſcription.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Firſt</hi> then, all they who may be truly ſaid to ſtudy to be quiet, will be ſure to have a ſpecial care o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver all their Actions, that they never offer any Injury to, or do any thing that may juſtly offend, or tend to moleſt others; but carefully endeavour to do as they would be done by, and to render unto every one his due, according to thoſe ſeveral Stations, either in Church or State, in which others ſtand related to them: But more eſpecially to be careful to behave themſelves reverently and obediently to the Supreme Magiſtrate, and towards all thoſe who are ſet in Authority under him, being <hi>ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to every Ordinance of Man, for the Lord's ſake;</hi> to pay Tribute and undergo the common Burdens chearfully; to ſuffer private Wrongs, where they cannot legally be redreſt, patiently, in order to the Publick Welfare and Advantage: To be far from doing any thing in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of, or oppoſition to Authority; but heartily to pray for their Governours, both Civil and Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal, and readily to comply with all the Laws of the Land wherein they live, where nothing is required of them inconſiſtent with any Law of God. In ſhort, to do nothing that is apt to breed Private Contentions, or Publick Broyls, nothing that tends to diſturb the Publick Peace, to change or ſubvert the Lawful Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment eſtabliſhed; nothing that would hinder the Reign of their Prince, from being ſafe, eaſie, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperous, or their Fellow-Subjects, from leading under
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:63795:8"/>
him, a quiet and a peaceable life, in all Godlineſs and Honeſty; but, on the contrary, to do all they can to promote the ſame. All this care now, over his Actions, muſt he have, who may be truly ſaid, <hi>to ſtudy to be quiet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And from hence now may appear how grosſly they endeavour to impoſe both upon themſelves and others, who, tho they have been guilty of all the Sedition and Diſorders, which directly lead to down-right blows, do yet call themſelves the moſt peaceable Perſons, and would fain be thought as quiet as Lambs, meerly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they have as yet abſtained from open Violence, and plain cutting of throats; as if nothing were ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to denominate men unquiet, leſs than being actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally up in Arms, and in open Rebellion againſt their Lawful Sovereign. Nay, time was, you know, and not ſo long ſince, when men of the ſame Principles, and many of the ſelf-ſame Perſons too, even at the ſame time that they were proceeding to all the higheſt De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees of Outrage and Hoſtility, and were actually ſwimming in a whole Sea of Innocent Blood of their own ſhedding, could yet have nothing but God and Religion, and the Goſpel in their Mouths, and pretend to do all this as the greateſt Lovers of Peace, and in order to promote the Publick. Well-fare and Tranqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity; impudently ſtyling themſelves, the King's <hi>most Dutiful and Loyal Subjects,</hi> at the ſame time, when they appeared in open Field againſt him, and in deſpite of all their own Cannons, loudly proclaiming to the World, and roaring them out the greateſt Liers and vileſt Hypocrites, that, perhaps, were ever yet permitted to be the Curſe of any Nation. Now, if any pretences whatſoever can make ſuch Practices as theſe conſiſtent with a peaceable Temper, or not to argue indeed the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:63795:8"/>
greateſt Contradiction in Men to all Study of being quiet, then no Men in the World ever yet were, or can ſtudy to be, unquiet. But certainly far leſs than this comes to, may juſtly make a Man deſerve this Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recter; and not only to be in open Rebellion; but even to refuſe to obey the wholeſom Laws of the Land, or for Men to promote Schiſm and Factions, Hatred and Animoſities, by cauſeleſsly withdrawing and unreaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nably ſeperating themſelves from the Publickly Eſtabliſht Worſhip, wherein nothing is Preſcribed or Practiſed contrary to the Word of God, this is as truly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiſtent with the Study of Peace, as any thing; as generally, and almoſt neceſſarily laying the Foundation of all other Unquietneſs, Sedition, and Confuſion. Whereas all they who truly ſtudy to be quiet, will carefully abſtain from this, or any other Action, which they know, will tend to deſtroy Peace and Charity, and ſow the Seeds of Diſcord and Contention among Brethren and Fellow Subjects.</p>
            <p>But <hi>Secondly,</hi> This Study alſo implys a watchful Care over our very Words, as well as Actions, of what we ſpeak or write, as well as how we behave our ſelves in other Particulars. For a Man may ſit ſtill and do nothing elſe, and yet ſo imploy his Tongue or Pen, as will no leſs effectually diſturb the Publick Peace, ſet Men by the Ears together, and even turn the World up-ſide down, then if in the Head of an Army, and actually making uſe of the moſt Warlike Preparations, to the ſame purpoſe. The Words of a cunning Incendiary have a ſtrange kind of Force and Influence, to the Poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoning and Inflaming of Men's minds; ſo that indeed, were it not for theſe, Men would ſcarce ever proceed to Blows. <hi>Behold</hi> (ſaith St. <hi>James) How great a matter,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:63795:9"/>
a little Fire kindleth. The Tongue is a Fire, a World of Iniquity</hi> [enough] <hi>to ſet on Fire the courſe of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</hi> All wiſe Magiſtrates have been ſo deeply ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of the extream Danger which there is, from the Liberty of unruly Tongues, that they have ever thought fit, in order to the ſecuring of the Publick Tranquility, to lay Reſtraints upon the ſame, by the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereſt Penalties, and to make Words as well as Actions Capital. And <hi>David</hi> brings in his Enemies vaunting, and placing no leſs Confidence in theſe, than in their very Arms, Pſ. 12. 4. <hi>With our Tongues</hi> (ſay they) <hi>will we prevail;</hi> and do our buſineſs, by the Force of Calumny. And the ſame Royal Prophet complains, Pſ. 57. 4. <hi>My Soul is among Lyons; and I lie even among them that are ſet on Fire; whoſe Teeth are Spears and Arrows</hi> (that is, as contributing towards their Speech) <hi>and their Tongue a ſharp Sword.</hi> And Pſ. 64. 3. <hi>who whet their Tongue like a Sword; and bend their Bow, to ſhoot their Arrows, even bitter Words.</hi> And indeed, Words there are of ſuch a curſed Nature and Effect, that they may be well lookt upon under the Notion of moſt Formidable Weapons; and as the very Files that ſerve to point all other Weapons, and to ſet an Edge alſo upon the Minds of the Rebellious Perſons that make uſe of them. Inſomuch, that what cruel Hatred Strife and Diſcords, what Murders, Seditions, Wars and Deſolations do not commonly, from hence, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed, as their true Cauſe, and unhappy Original? So true is that of Ecclus. 28. 14. 18. <hi>A Back-biting Tongue hath diſquieted many, and driven them from Nation to Nation; ſtrong Cities hath it pulled down, and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrown the Houſes of great Men. Many have fallen by the Edge of the Sword, but not ſo many as have fallen by the Tongue.</hi> But we of this Nation have ſadly been in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:63795:9"/>
in the late Civil Wars, and had now like once again to have Experienced, what ſad Feats may be Effected, by the Power of Licencious Tongues and Pens. For from the abuſed Pulpits and Preſſes chiefly ſounded the Shrileſt Trumpets, and Effectual Alarms, to that Curſed Rebellion; Theſe were the main deadly En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gines of Battery and Confuſion; theſe were the very Magazines, which furniſhed them, with all that Hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Artillery, of the moſt Horrid Lies, Slanders, and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumnies, of the moſt unreaſonable Suſpitions, Fears, and Jealouſies, which made Men perfectly Diſtracted, and fall to the Butchering ſo of one another, and at laſt to the Barbarous Murder of one of the beſt Princes that ever ſway'd Scepter. And indeed as long as Men are ſuffered ſtill ſo much to make uſe of the ſame Chavel'd Bullets, the like Poyſoned unlawful Weapons, there can be no Hopes of ſecuring any laſting Peace or Tranquility among us<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Nor can any one be eſteemed o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than <hi>a troubler of our Iſrael,</hi> who makes no Conſcience of his Words, <hi>to keep his Tongue from Evil, and his Lips that they ſpeak no Guile.</hi> For the ſame may be ſaid of Peaceableneſs, which<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> St. <hi>James</hi> affirms of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion in general; <hi>If any Man among you would ſeem</hi> or be thought <hi>to study to be quiet, and bridleth not his Tongue, that Man does but deceive his own Heart,</hi> and all his Pretences to Quietneſs are altogether vain.</p>
            <p>Nay <hi>Thirdly,</hi> He that may be truly ſaid to ſtudy to be quiet, muſt be careful alſo over his very Thoughts, and Wiſhes, and moſt ſecret Deſigns; not to deſire or me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditate within himſelf, any thing injurious, or which tends to the Perjudice, or cauſeleſs<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Diſturbance of any of his Neighbours<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> much leſs any thing which would un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſettle the Government, or be Inconſiſtent with the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:63795:10"/>
of the Publick Peace, and Common Well-fare. For it many times may, and does ſo happen, that under a more ſtrict Government, a man may be ſo o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver-awed, through the fear of Puniſhment, as to lay ſome Reſtraints upon his Words and Actions, and to be care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful of what he does, and what, and to whom he ſays anything, meerly for want of a ſafe Opportunity of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>having himſelf otherwiſe: Whileſt his Heart is full of that Treaſon and Sedition, which will be ſure to break out and openly ſhew it ſelf as ſoon as ever the Man ſuppoſeth he has met with a more ſecure Seaſon. But they who are truly Peaceable, will be careful alſo to have a Peaceable Mind, ready always moſt heartily to pray for the Peace of their <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and for the Safety and Proſperity alſo of all thoſe lawful Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, whoſe Buſineſs it is to ſecure its Tranquillity; will be far from <hi>curſing the King ſo much as in their Hearts;</hi> for let Mens <hi>Words be ſmoother than Butter</hi> (as the Pſalmiſt Phraſeth it) yet whileſt <hi>War is in their Hearts;</hi> this is ſufficient to denominate Men Enemies unto Peace; as being indeed, in it ſelf, a moſt direct Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction to all Study of being quiet.</p>
            <p>Nor is it yet ſufficient for a Man to take care of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf only, unleſs (in the laſt Place) he endeavour, as much as in him lies, that all other Men alſo may be alike Peaceably diſpoſed and demean themſelves. For 'tis poſſible for a Man to ſit ſtill, and neither to do, nor ſay any thing himſelf, which may immediately denominate him a Diſturber of the Publick Tranquil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, and yet whileſt, by any means, he willingly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fords Incouragement or Opportunity of Succeſs, to thoſe that are ſo, the ſame Man does no leſs effectually con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute to the inſuing Diſturbance, than if he had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo immediately buſied himſelf to the ſame Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe.
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:63795:10"/>
'Tis much the ſame thing for one to do Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief immediately by himſelf, or through the means of ſome other third Perſon, by him enabled and ſet on to do it. The main difference is only, that the one does it uſually more<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſecurely, as to himſelf, and always more ſlily, Baſely, and Treacherouſly than the other.</p>
            <p>And they who, as far as they dare, make it their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Practice underhand to favour and encourage o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, in their Vile Miſrepreſentations of the Deſigns, in their blaſting the Reputation, and weak'ning the Hands of thoſe that are the true Lovers of, and Endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourers after Peace; and, on the other Hand, make it their Buſineſs, to conceal, ſtand up for, defend, countenance, and excuſe the Seditious Words and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of others, whoſe Deſign it is to ſet all in a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſtion, ſuch Favourers and Abettors are indeed no leſs dangerous or Innocent, than the moſt open and decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Enemies to the publick Well-fare and Tranquillity. Nay, in ſhort, for a Man<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to ſtand ſtill only as a Sly Squinting<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Neuter, and not heartily to joyn with, help, and ſtrengthen (as much as he can) the Intereſt, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation, and Authority of all thoſe who truly endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to be quiet, and maintain Peace: or, on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, not to do his beſt to detect, diſcourage, and hinder the wicked Counſels and Attempts of all thoſe who evidently make it their Buſineſs to create Diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bance and Confuſion, either in Church or State, even this alſo, is wholy inconſiſtent with the Real Study of being quiet.</p>
            <p>And thus having done with the firſt Enquiry, I proceed now to the ſecond General thing I propoſed, <hi>viz.</hi> to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider and briefly to demonſtrate what abſolute neceſſity there is of the moſt earneſt Study and Contrivance, of the moſt diligent Care and Circumſpection to be uſed,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:63795:11"/>
by all thoſe who would indeed lead a quiet and a peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Life.</p>
            <p>Now there are theſe two Things chiefly, which, when they happen to meet together, do always make it abſolutely neceſſary for us, to beſtow the utmoſt of our Care and Diligence, about the Attainment of any Qualification; and that is, when the Qualification it ſelf is of great Excellency and of higheſt Importance to be attained, and yet, 'tis moſt certain, cannot be attained, without much Difficulty. But now both theſe Properties or Conditions are eminently Conſpicuous and Demonſtrable in the preſent Duty which we are diſcourſing of.</p>
            <p>For <hi>Firſt,</hi> as for the ſingular Excellence and high Importance of a quiet and peaceable Behaviour, the Scripture is every where ſo very plain and Pregnant to this purpoſe, that none but a meer Infidel can, in the leaſt, doubt of the thing. <hi>David</hi> was ſo raviſhed with the ſweet Contemplation of it, that he crys out in perfect Admiration, <hi>Behold, how good and pleaſant a thing it is, for Brethren to dwell together in <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity!</hi> Nor indeed does God himſelf (who alone beſt knows how both to value and reward our ſeveral Perfections) more highly eſteem of any thing, than of this bleſſed Temper; St. <hi>Peter</hi> aſſuring us, <hi>that a meek and quiet Spirit is, in the ſight of God, of great price,</hi> 1 Pet. 3. 4. And are not theſe the very Words of him, who ſhall, at laſt, pronounce every Man's Final Sentence either to Woe, or Happineſs? <hi>Bleſſed are the Peace-makers; for they ſhall be called</hi> (That is, eſteemed and rewarded as) <hi>the Children of God?</hi> Does not our bleſſed Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our himſelf likewiſe, make this the ſtanding Infallible Mark and diſlinguiſhing Character of a Chriſtian or Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuine
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:63795:11"/>
Diſciple? <hi>By this ſhall all Men know that ye are my Diſciples, if ye love one another.</hi> And according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly St. <hi>Paul,</hi> in like manner, could not deſire Men to give a better Evidence of <hi>their Walking worthy of the Vocation, wherewith they are called,</hi> that is of their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>having themſelves as Chriſtians than by their endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavouring <hi>to keep the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of the Spirit, in the Bond of Peace;</hi> as it may appear, by the Connexion of the Firſt and Third Verſe of the Fourth Chapter to the <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So we find <hi>Love</hi> and <hi>Peace</hi> reckoned up as the main Fruits of the Spirit: Whereas <hi>Hatred, Variance, Emu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, Wrath, Strife, and Seditions</hi> are put among the Manifeſt and Notorious Works of the Fleſh, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5. 19. 22. And St. <hi>Paul</hi> Appeals to thoſe who give them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves up to ſuch Vices, as Perſons ſelf-condemned, for no better than meer Carnal-men, and ſuch as are far e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough from having any thing of the true Chriſtian Spirit and Goſpel Temper, 1 Cor. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. 3. <hi>Whereas there is among you Envying, and Strife, and Diviſions, are ye not carnal, and walk as men?</hi> St. <hi>James</hi> alſo tells us plainly, <hi>That where Envying and Strife is, there is Confuſion, and every evil Work,</hi> 1 Jam. 3. 16, 17.</p>
            <p>In ſhort, How frequently, and with what Earneſtneſs are we every where called upon, <hi>To follow after the things which make for Peace; to let the Peace of God Rule in our hearts?</hi> How full are all the Holy Writings of the New Teſtament of Precepts and Exhortations, to this purpoſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And were there no other, methinks, that of St. <hi>Paul</hi> might be ſufficient, to all who in earn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt believe a future State; when he expresſly aſſures us, from God himſelf, that, <hi>without following after Peace</hi> as well as <hi>Holineſs,</hi> in the General, <hi>No man ſhall ever ſee the Lord,</hi> Heb. 12. 14.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:63795:12"/>So that, indeed, if all the Promiſes, or Threatnings, if all the Commendations, Exhortations, or Commands of the Goſpel be of force enough to make a thing ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary; if it be of any importance to us, whether we be real Chriſtians or no; whether we be Spiritual, or Carnal; ſuch as Chriſt will, at laſt, approve of, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn; In a word, if either our preſent Happineſs here in this life, or our eternal Happineſs hereafter be thought things worth our looking after; it muſt then alſo be of higheſt Concern to us, that we be of a quiet Temper, and be found ſuch as behave themſelves peaceably.</p>
            <p>Nor can we poſſibly uſe too great Diligence about this. Eſpecially if we conſider alſo, how many Rubs and Hinderances we are like to meet with in the way, and how difficultly it is attainable.</p>
            <p>Many indeed who are but little acquainted with themſelves, and with the World, may be apt enough to imagine, that to be quiet and peaceable is no ſuch hard matter, as that it ſhould require in men ſo much Care and Study to keep themſelves ſo. <hi>For does not Quietneſs</hi> (may they ſay) <hi>conſist chiefly in Negatives? And is it not much eaſier, in the general, to ſit ſtill, and not to act, than to be buſily employed in Action? So that, after a man has but once a mind to be quiet; what ſhould hinder him from ſo behaving himſelf? or how ſhould there be any ſuch great Difficulty in this Affair?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But yet when ſuch men come indeed to the Practice and Experiment, they may ſoon be convinced of their Errour, and fully ſatisfied that all the Care and Contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance they can uſe, to keep themſelves peaceable, is little enough. For though indeed, <hi>but to have a mind to be quiet,</hi> will go a great way in the thing, and though it be in it ſelf alſo more eaſie, as well as more happy and delightful for a man to be peaceable, than to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>governable
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:63795:12"/>
and contentious; yet ſuch is the ſtrange Corruption of our Nature, ſuch, and ſo many are the Hinderances and Temptations, both from within, and without us, that it ſeems almoſt impoſſible for any one to be truly quiet, and much more that he ſhould long continue ſo, by chance, but, as the World goes, he that would indeed be ſo, muſt be ſure <hi>to take a great deal of pains to be quiet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For Firſt, Every Luſt you are willing to harbour in your hearts, will certainly prove a Make-bate and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendiary, which will never ſuffer you to be long quiet: but, forcing you to break all your Reſolutions for Peace, be ſure to ingage you in endleſs Broyls and Contentions. But now how hard and laborious a Task it is, and what great Care and Diligence muſt be uſed, to conquer and ſubdue a man's own Luſts, all will eaſily acknowledge, who have been, in the leaſt acquainted with the Work of Mortification.</p>
            <p>But ſtill, beſides this Treacherous Brood, of his own Houſe-hold, which every man has more or leſs With<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in himſelf, we are alſo continually ſurrounded from without, with whole multitudes of ſuch as are ſworn Enemies unto Peace; who will be ſure, if poſſible, to hinder us from following it. The Devil and all his wicked Inſtruments are always ſtrangely buſie, in ſow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Seeds of Hatred, Diſcord, and Contention, and the World is every where full of ſuch Perſons, who, as they are themſelves extremely Peeviſh, Diſcontented, and Ungovernable; ſo is it their very Study and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment (as much as they can by all means) to draw in, and make others become like them. And that good man has found out a happy Dwelling-place indeed, whoſe heart finds not occaſion frequently to ſigh out
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:63795:13"/>
that Complaint of <hi>David; My Soul hath long dwelt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them that are Enemies unto Peace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He that would keep himſelf quiet will be forced to be at the trouble of often ſuſpending his Belief, of ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping his Ears, of ſhifting his Company, and changing his Acquaintance. And yet, when all is done, you muſt contentedly expect to be mortally hated and ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, to be injured and reviled, and lookt upon as ſtrange Monſters, by the Sons of Wrath and Bitterneſs, merely becauſe you will not run, with them, into the ſame Exceſs of Riot and Sedition. For if, with <hi>David,</hi> you ſincerely endeavour to maintain Peace, you will be ſure to meet with thoſe alſo, who, as ſoon as ever you ſpeak to them thereof, will be ſo much the more enra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged thereat againſt you, as preſently to make them rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy for Battle. In ſhort, they who are <hi>the real Troublers of Iſrael</hi> themſelves, will not fail to call you, by this odious name, and to treat you as ſuch, upon no other account, but becauſe you refuſe to joyn with them, in being ſo indeed.</p>
            <p>Nay, the Devil has of late, made uſe of one powerful Stratagem and Temptation, which ſeems, indeed, beyond all others; and is ſuch as, I'm perſwaded, has moſt ſtart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and rendred it extreamly difficult, even for ſeveral well-meaning men, to keep themſelves peaceable. And this he has effected, by inſpiring a ſort of leading Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrites among us, who, whilſt they pretend them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves the only Zealots for, and Profeſſors of the true Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, have indeed ſet up a New Goſpel of their own, ſo directly oppoſite, in this, to that which our Saviour and his Apoſtles delivered, that, according to the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of theſe men; He muſt preſently be ſtigmatized, as an Enemy to the <hi>Truth,</hi> who is careful to continue a Friend unto <hi>Peace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:63795:13"/>Nor will <hi>their Goſpel allow</hi> any one to be <hi>truly Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous,</hi> who is, at the ſame time, <hi>truly Peaceable:</hi> but that ſtudy of Love, and mutual Peace, which our Saviour makes the mark of a true Diſciple, they endeavour to turn into the Character of one who ſecretly adores An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt; whilſt what St. <hi>Jude</hi> attributes to the firſt grand Hereticks, <hi>The diſpiſing of Dominions, and ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing evil of Dignities, and refuſing to be ſubject to any lawful Authority, either for wrath or conſcience ſake,</hi> goes, with them, for the moſt ſubſtantial Argument of an Orthodox Profeſſour, and only true Believer. In a word, under the pretence of Religion, they have done their utmoſt to deſtroy the very Life and Soul of it; And, if what theſe men (as I ſhall hereafter ſhew) have both preach'd and lately printed, were indeed the Goſpel, our Saviour muſt then have bequeathed to all his Diſciples, not that bleſſed Legaſie <hi>of Peace,</hi> but nothing but War, Diſcord, and Confuſion, from Generation to Generation; and have come into the World only to turn men into Wolves and Tigers, to ſubvert all good Order, and ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to diſſolve all Civil Society, among the Sons of Men.</p>
            <p>But now ſince ſuch Doctrines as have this direct ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency are both taught and maintained, by thoſe who would be thought the moſt faithful Miniſters of the Goſpel; and ſince there are alſo ſo many other Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations and Diſcouragements that render it ſo extreme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly difficult, for men to behave themſelves peaceably; how infinitely therefore does it concern every ſincere Chriſtian to arm himſelf againſt them, and carefully to look about him? How highly neceſſary is it for us, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that is, as the Word implies, to ſtudy and endeavour to be quiet, with the ſame earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and ſolicitude, as the moſt ambitious Perſons do, in
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:63795:14"/>
the purſuit after Honours and Preferment, or with the like Concern, which may be obſerved in the moſt Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetous, to heap up Riches; that is, to endeavour after Peace with the moſt Exquiſite Care and Diligence ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginable.</p>
            <p>And ſo I proceed now to the <hi>Third</hi> General thing, <hi>viz.</hi> To endeavour to ſhew, how this Study of ours may be beſt directed; or, in what Particulars chiefly, our Care to this purpoſe may moſt ſucceſsfully be employed. And now in Order to this, let me, in the firſt place direct you, as the main Foundation of all Peace and Quietneſs, to endeavour to be fully convinced of the Truth of Chriſtianity and to have alſo your Minds and Hearts fully poſſeſt with the continual Conſideration of thoſe Glorious Rewards and Happineſs of that future State, which the <hi>Son</hi> of God came into <hi>the World</hi> to acquaint us with, and prepare us for. Seek but firſt, in good earneſt, the Kingdom of God and his Righteouſneſs; place your main Treaſure and Happineſs in Heaven, and in thoſe Qualifications which may fit you for it; and then where your Treaſure is, there will your Heart be alſo. And he that is thus ſincere in Religion, and has once got Heaven into his Heart; muſt neceſſarily ſo little value all elſe, as that it will be impoſſible, he ſhould fall out about any earthly things; the exceſſive Love of which is always the Cauſe and true Root of all Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rrels and Contentions. He that is fond of the World, or dotes upon any thing here below, will never fail upon infinite Occaſions, of being engaged, in endleſs Broiles and Conteſts; whileſt Heavenly-mindedneſs is the only thing that can render Men contented, and effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually ſecure them in Peace. And our Saviour is therefore indeed the great Author and Promoter of Peace, among Men, not only in that he has every
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:63795:14"/>
where ſo ſtrictly commanded them to maintain the ſame; but chiefly, in that they who heartily embrace his Religion, are powerfully enabled, through the firm Belief and Conſideration of the life to come, to wean themſelves from, and ſet looſe to the things of this; ſetting their Affections on the things above, and not on the things beneath; otherwiſe all his Commands of following Peace, would have been impracticable, and but to little purpoſe. Whileſt now, nothing is more eaſie or natural, than the Obſervation of theſe Precepts, after once a Vigorous faith has pluckt up out of Men's Hearts, that bitter Root of all Contention, Worldly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mindedneſs. And therefore it is not at all ſo ſtrange, that the Primitive Chriſtians ſhould live in ſuch Peace together and bleſſed Concord, as to be of one Heart, and of one Soul, when the full Perſuaſion and Belief of the eternal Happineſs of another Life, had ſo per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly raſed out of their Hearts, (that very Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of all Diſcord) the love of Worldly things, that they could afford to <hi>think nothing of the things they poſſeſſed, their own, but to have all things common, ſelling their Goods, and imparting them to all, as eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Man had need,</hi> as we read, <hi>Act.</hi> 4. 32. 8. <hi>c.</hi> 2. 45. Which extraordinary and miraculous Example of theirs, tho it does not hinder (unleſs the like Circumſtances ſhould alſo require the ſame of us) but that Chriſtians now may both lawfully and conveniently maintain a Propriety in theſe temporal Good Things; yet, as the ſame Belief will make us always ready cheerfully to diſtribute to thoſe that have need, as Chriſtian-pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence may direct us, ſo will it be ſure to keep us from any ſuch fondneſs towards Worldly Good Things, as would engage us to ſacrifice Peace; but we ſhall be far enough from diſturbing the World, or injuring
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:63795:15"/>
any<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Perſon, in order to the keeping or encreaſing our Poſſeſſions. 'Tis nothing elſe but their Pride, Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſs, or Ambition, that makes Men Reſtleſs and Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiet, and ſets them ſo at difference; for <hi>from whence come Wars and Fightings</hi> (ſaith St. <hi>James) come they not hence even of your Luſts, which war in your Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers?</hi> Theſe, theſe are the <hi>real Penſioners</hi> that betray the Peace and Happineſs of a Nation or Society; theſe are the things that make Men firſt uneaſie within themſelves, and then troubleſome to others. Upon which account therefore, the Prophet, compares wicked Men, to <hi>the troubled Sea, when it cannot rest, whoſe Waters cast up Mire and Dirt.</hi> If. 57. 20. But let us take care only, by that purifying Hope, which ought to be, and is in every real Chriſtian, to regulate our corrupt Affections, and mortify our Fleſhly Deſires, and then, when our <hi>Jonas</hi>-luſts are once caſt from us, all the former Storms and Tempeſts of Contention will ſoon ceaſe, and the reſt of our Voyage beſure to prove Calm and Peaceable.</p>
            <p>He who ſo ſeriouſly believes the Goſpel, as to place his Hopes, his Treaſure, and his Heart in Heaven, muſt needs have Active Peace with all the World. For firſt, ſuch a one, to be ſure, can have no manner of Occaſion, or poſſibility of Temptation, either to Envy, Hate, or fall out with any other, upon the account of ſpiritual Good Things; becauſe he knows it is impoſſible that any Man in the World, without his own conſent, ſhould either injure him in, or hinder him of that Happineſs, in the Hopes of which he can reſt perfectly well con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented: And then, as for any temporal things, his Heart is too much engaged elſe where, nor does he value them at ſuch a rate, as that, for the ſake of thoſe, he ſhould become Quarrelſome, and Unpeaceable; eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:63795:15"/>
ſince he well knows, that his ſo behaving him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf about ſuch Trifles, would moſt certainly hinder him, of that future Happineſs, for which alone, he is ſo mainly, and heartily concerned. So that let Men colour their Deſigns as they will, let them endeavour to deceive others, and, perhaps, their own Hearts, as much as they can, with the vain Pretences of meer zeal for Religion; there can be no ſuch thing in the caſe, whileſt Men are Peeviſh, and Quarrelſome, Sediti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and Ungovernable; nothing but Mammon, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but Pride, Covetouſneſs, or Ambition, and what is moſt contrary to the Goſpel, is really at the bottom of ſuch Mens Hearts, and that which indeed puts them upon ſuch Practices and unquiet Behaviour; they are far from having yet believed or conſidered things, like true Chriſtians.</p>
            <p>In ſhort, if we look, not only on bare Names, but upon things themſelves; a Worldly minded Man, or an unpeaceable, or difloyal Chriſtian, is no leſs Nonſenſe and a Contradiction, than a Spiritual-ſenſualiſt, a juſt Robber, or an innocent Murderer. Whereas he who does really believe, and endeavours ſtill more and more to ſtrengthen and confirm his perſuaſion con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the other Life; he who has his Heart above, and makes it his earneſt Study to mortify his Luſts; that Man does alſo, in the ſame, moſt effectually ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and take the moſt ſucceſsful courſe in the World, to be quiet.</p>
            <p>But Secondly, in order to this excellent purpoſe, have a ſpecial care what you uſe to hear, and read, and with what kind of Company you enter into any Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liarity: For otherwiſe, let a man be never ſo peaceably inclined, it will he wholly impoſſible for him long to
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:63795:16"/>
continue quiet. 'Tis natural for men to colour with their Company, and with the froward to learn Froward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. Such as thy Companions are, ſuch wilt thou alſo ſoon be thy ſelf. More men are poyſoned, by the way of the ears, and from what comes from other men's mouths, than from what enters in at their own. And he who feeds upon nothing but ſtinking Carrion, and takes in nothing but tainted and moſt unwholſom<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Meat and Drink, may as well expect to retain a ſound and healthful Conſtitution, as that man a quiet peaceable Mind; who can allow himſelf to be great and intimate only with thoſe that are of a factious turbulent Spirit, and of ſeditious Principles; for by frequent and familiar converſe with ſuch Perſons, 'tis natural and neceſſary for a man inſenſibly to receive the like Impreſſions and Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions of things, to imbibe the ſame Hopes, and Fears, Jealouſies and Suſpicions, and, by degrees, to be wholly moved and carried on by the ſame Diſcontents, Prejudices and Diſaffections. And what can be expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted of any ſuch Perſon, whoſe Acquaintance or Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons hap'ning to be chiefly of thoſe that are notoriouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Factious and Diſcontented, does, by his open ears and credulous heart, give a ready entertainment to what they infuſe, and make himſelfe (as it were) the Sink or Common Shore, of all the accurſed Lies and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumnies, of all the falſe Stories and malicious Inſinuati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and of the reſt of that filth and excrement of their cankred Minds, which the whole Party ſhall at any time think fit to void, on purpoſe to caſt in the Face of the Government, and to render all thoſe odious, who faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully endeavour to uphold it? whither will not ſuch a Man be, at laſt, hurried, through the Influence of ſuch ill Company, tho otherwiſe, of himſelf, never ſo peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably inclined? Nay indeed a Man runs a very great Hazard in being intimate but with any one ſingle Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:63795:16"/>
that is of this ſour leven. And therefore let the Courteſies Received, or to be Expected from ſuch a one be never ſo Conſiderable to thee, let his Reputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for Parts or Piety be never ſo great; after the Man has evidently Diſcovered to thee, by any one or more deliberate ill Actions, that he is not ſincere, nor a real Friend to Peace, but of a Reſtleſs Ambitious Temper, and a great Favourer of thoſe, who, in Purſuit of the like. Deſigns, would be glad to put all into Confuſion; and thou perceiveſt withal no likelyhood of his being reclaimed by thee; whatſoever it coſts thee then, be ſure to break looſe from him, as ſoon, and as civilly as you can: for ſuch a one can no longer be ſafely made a Friend or Familiar, by him, who would ſucceſsfully ſtudy to be quiet.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> As another excellent courſe to keep your ſelves quiet and peaceable, Be ſure to make Conſcience of avoiding Idleneſs, and be careful to ſerve God and your Countrey, by diligently employing your ſelves every one in his proper and lawful Calling. Idleneſs is in it ſelf a very melancholick diſcontented thing, na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally apt to breed, in Men, many Luſts and great Poverty, to make them need and deſire more than other Men, and yet to have leſs; and ſo, prove to put them upon any the moſt violent and injurious Courſes, by a ſhort and eaſie cut, to make out their deſired For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune. And indeed, were there nothing elſe in it, he that will not employ himſelf as he ought, will ſoon fall to buſie himſelf in doing Miſchief. So true is that of the Son of <hi>Syrach,</hi> Ecclus. 33. 27. <hi>Idleneſs teacheth much Evil.</hi> And accordingly, had not <hi>Pharoah</hi> been Tyrannical, in the unreaſonable Tasks he impoſed, he was not out in his Politicks, when, to ſecure his fears of
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:63795:17"/>
the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi>'s making Head againſt him, he thought it his beſt Courſe to take care, that they ſhould all be continually imployed in Labour. And moſt Governments and Common-Wealths have wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thought fit to provide for the Security of the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Peace and Tranquillity, by making Laws to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent Idleneſs, under very ſevere Penalties. Nor is it any other than a very obvious Obſervation, how ſuch kind of Perſons generally are the main Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, both of more private Miſchiefs, and of Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Diſturbances, whom Idleneſs, and her attendent Luſts, and diſcontented Poverty, has firſt prepared for ſuch wicked Undertakings. And what one of the late Traytors alſo (who ſeemed to die more like a penitent than any of the reſt) does, in his laſt Speech, caution others to this purpoſe, is well wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy the ſerious notice, and timely Conſideration of ſeveral among us, who are but too notoriouſly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned in that particular. But thus much, I hope, may ſuffice to make you ſenſible, how great an Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my to Quietneſs is Idleneſs; and on the contrary, how good a help and expedient is Diligence in an honeſt Calling and Employment.</p>
            <p>Which brings me now directly to the particular means, which we are here ſo expresſly directed to, in the Text, to this very purpoſe, <hi>Mind your own Buſineſs.</hi> Which we are to underſtand as an uſeful Caution, in Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition not only to Idleneſs, but chiefly to that prag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matical Temper, or idle Buſineſs, when men will not keep within their own proper Sphere and Compaſs; but intrude themſelves into other men's Affairs, and become buſie-bodies in other men's Matters, which they ought not any way to be ſo concerned in. Which Vice, becauſe it is ſo general and epidemical, and yet
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:63795:17"/>
commonly apt to be thought harmleſs enough and inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent; I ſhall therefore think it worth the while a little more largely to ſhew the ſeveral other great Follies and Miſchiefs of it in general, as well as its direct Repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nancy to all Peace and Quietneſs, in particular. And this now I ſhall endeavour to perform, from theſe fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Arguments or Conſiderations.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> He that buſies himſelf in other men's matters, will be forced to neglect his own proper Buſineſs and Calling, by the due following of which he might be ſure of being moſt happy and ſucceſsful, and through the neglect of which, he uſually makes himſelf miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for the preſent, and muſt be ſure to give a ſevere ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, for ſuch his neglect, hereafter. Every man has enough to do, to acquit himſelf conſcionably, and like a Chriſtian, in the diligent diſcharge of thoſe ſeveral Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties required of him, in that particular Sphere and Stati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, in which it has pleaſed God to place him. The mind of man is ſo finite, and our Stength and Abilities ſo limited and confined, that ſcarce any man is fit ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesſfully to undertake, at the ſame time, many and diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Employments: But he that ſtands fixt in his own proper place, and diligently applies himſelf to the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing of that particular Employment only, which God's Providence, in the direction of his own firſt Choice, and the Care of his Relations, has called him to, ſeldom or never fails of very good ſucceſs therein. Whereas that man who intermeddles with every matter, and endeavours to be ſomebody, in every thing, is very ſeldom extraordinary in any thing; and many times is grosſly defective, and unhappy, in that particular thing, which is his proper Profeſſion, and of which it is greatly both ſhameful and inconvenient for him to be
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:63795:18"/>
either ignorant or neglectful. And what can be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable to the Folly of thoſe men, who incumber and diſtract their Minds about many things, who waſt their time and ſtrength in vain, about what belongs not at all to them, about ſuch things, as they might both ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and with much Benefit both to themſelves and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, let alone; and at the ſame time are wholly care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs of doing their Duties, in that particular Province, which yet cannot, without their great Sin and Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, be ſo neglected? And when, at length, by this mean's (as it uſually comes to paſs) ſuch fond Pragmati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co's have greatly diſturbed the Peace of the Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and have brought Infamy, Poverty, and Miſery upon themſelves and their Families, even in this World, and come at the laſt day to give an account of their Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lents and Behaviour; What a wretchedly ridiculous Plea will it be for them to alledge, We were ſo very much buſied in inſtructing of our Teachers, and in cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recting the Faults of our Magiſtrates; ſo wholly taken up about State Affairs, and in directing of our Superi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours how to govern us, or the like, that we were for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to forget the Obedience of Subjects, and could find no time for that neceſſary diligence which we ſhould have exerciſed in our own proper Callings? Thus, may not that of the Son of <hi>Syrach,</hi> be juſtly applied, to all ſuch ſelf-conceited buſie-bodies in other men's Matters? Eccluſ. 27. 19. <hi>There are thoſe that are wiſe, and teach many, and yet are unprofitable to themſelves.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Such a one uſually miſpends his time and ſtrength to no purpoſe; in buſying himſelf about ſuch things, as he cannot, ordinarily, underſtand, nor is any way fitly qualified to mannage. The different Birth, natural Parts, Cuſtom, and Education of men, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:63795:18"/>
(in all theſe) Providence it ſelf ſeems ſo to have deſigned ſome to one only, and ſome to another, this man to a meaner, and that to a higher Office, in the Common-wealth, that 'tis ordinarily the greateſt wiſdom and trueſt Intereſt, for each Perſon to keep cloſe only to that particular Vocation, which he at firſt pitched upon, and has, for any conſiderable time, applied himſelf to. Whilſt they who do otherwiſe, do commonly but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray, and find, at laſt, ſufficient cauſe to repent their Fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. Every man is not cut out for every Employment, and yet 'tis a common Folly for moſt men to think themſelves better fitted, to do the Buſineſs of others, than their own. And, O what a profound Divine, what an excellent Preacher could I make? ſaith the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chanick; and how admirably well could I perform the Office of a Judge, a Magiſtrate, Privy-Counceller, or Prince? ſaith the inferiour Tradeſman; for as to their own Profeſſion, Experience has taught them, that there are in it ſeveral Difficulties; whilſt in thoſe of other men, meer Blindneſs makes them bold, and Ignorance confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent; and when they are not able to ſee the Difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, ſoon conclude, that there are none, but that all is ſmooth and eaſie. Thus even the moſt dull and block<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh Perſons, who have ever been no better than meer Bunglers in their own proper buſineſs, and have ſcarce Capacity enough to underſtand or go through with the meaneſt Profeſſion, are yet many times the moſt pert and medleſome, in the Affairs of other men, and apt to think themſelves moſt fit to undertake ſuch high and difficult Employments, towards the worthy diſcharge of which, indeed, even the choiceſt natural and beſt improved Parts, the largeſt Time, Diligence, Study and Experience, are all little enough rightly to qualifie and enable a man. <hi>How can he get wiſedom</hi> (ſaith the Son
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:63795:19"/>
of <hi>Syrach, Eccluſ.</hi> 38. 25.) <hi>that holdeth the Plow, and that glorieth in the Goad, that driveth Oxen, and is occu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pied in their Labours, and whoſe talk is of Bullocks, &amp;c.</hi> The ſame incapacity likewiſe he afterwards affirms, to be in the Carpender, Graver of Seals, Smith, Potter; concerning whom and the like Artificers, he concludes in the 31, and 33, Verſe; <hi>All theſe truſt to their hands, and every one is wiſe in his own work; but they ſhall not be ſought for in Publick Council, nor ſit high in the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation; they ſhall not ſit on the Judges Seat, nor un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the Sentence of Judgment; they cannot declare Juſtice and Judgment, and they ſhall not be found where Parables are ſpoken.</hi> We might alſo inſtance in ſeveral other leſs conſiderable Occupations, which though they may not be, perhaps, altogether unuſeful (as the ſame Author ſpeaks) <hi>towards the maintaining the State of the World;</hi> yet it can hardly ſeem poſſible, how the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors of the ſame ſhould ever, without immediate In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiration, <hi>attain to that wiſdom of the Learned, which ordinarily cometh only through opportunity of leiſure.</hi> Nor can I, for my part, very eaſily diſcover (though al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways ready to ſubmit to more diſcerning Judgments) what great Kindred or Analogie there can be, between the skill of rightly compoſing of a Bruſh, and that of ordering the Commonwealth; and I am very apt to think it poſſible for one who has made this his conſtant buſineſs, to know well enough how to make a Bird-cage, and yet be no very fit man to determine the deepeſt and moſt controverted Points in Divinity, nor over well verſed in the <hi>Arcana Imperii.</hi> And, methinks, I cannot but fancy it to look a little Ridiculous, that one who has attained skill enough conveniently to wire-in a ſilly Parrat, and has got a trick, like it, to talk by roat, and without underſtanding of Religion, ſhould immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:63795:19"/>
eſteem himſelf a Saint, take heart upon it, and from hence conceit, that he has both the <hi>Skill</hi> and <hi>Call</hi> alſo <hi>to bind Kings themſelves in Chains, and their Nobles in Fetters of Iron.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Even where ſuch Perſons do happen com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petently to underſtand, and have Skill and Parts enough to manage what they undertake, yet when, without any regular Call to it, they ſo intrude themſelves into other men's Affairs and Provinces, which no way be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to them, they are ſeldom or never ſucceſsful there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in. I readily acknowledge that ſome Perſons one may obſerve, whoſe minds may ſeem too great for that mean part, which Providence has given them to Act here on this World's Theater; ſome, whoſe natural Parts are ſuch as, to which had there but been added the advantage of a ſuitable Education, might have qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lified them for any thing; nor can it be denied, that ſome, though, rarely even in the meaneſt Occupations, make a ſhift to ſteal ſo much time, to attain to ſuch con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable Improvements of Nature's Stock, as may ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der them very capable of no ordinary Station or Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment in the Commonwealth; and there want not Examples, of ſuch Perſons, who when they have been regularly called, by Authority, to ſuch higher Offices, have proved ſingularly uſeful to the Publick: But yet let their Knowledge and Abilities be what they can, when men who have all along profeſſed a meaner, or much different Occupation, ſhall of their own heads, buſily intrude themſelves to act in the Affairs of a high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Station, there are theſe three things, that commonly hinder them from any good Succeſs in the diſcharge thereof.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:63795:20"/>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> Such Perſons are ſure to labour under no ſmall Envy and Prejudice, and very much to want that general Reputation and Truſt, from others, without which they can ſcarce have an opportunity of doing any great matters. Men are naturally moſt relyed upon and truſted for their Skill in that Art or Profeſſion, which they are known all along to have made their Buſineſs; Whilſt Upſtarts and Intruders, are as generally pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed, without any more ado, to be raw and unskil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, in their new Employments and Undertakings. So that the one, having more Truſt and Credit, though poſſibly leſs Skill and Parts, are more reſorted to, and better ſucceed than the other; who, though furniſhed ſometimes with greater Abilities, yet wanting the neceſſary Credit thereof, are therefore commonly neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected and contemned.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Though ſuch Uſurpers may have know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and Abilities, ſufficient for the diſcharge of thoſe employments, into which they ſo unreaſonably intrude themſelves: Yet they ſeldom have the Will or Deſire ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely to make uſe of the ſame, towards the publick Benefit, but only to the ſatisfaction of their own particular Luſts; and as Pride, Covetouſneſs, or Ambition, firſt puts them upon the Undertaking, ſo they commonly behave them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves accordingly all along, moſt unhappily and extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vagantly. Laſtly, God himſelf is ſo much a friend to the Obſervance of that neceſſary Order, without which Government and humane Society cannot be well main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, that for the more effectual diſcountenance of all Attempts to the contrary, he ſeldom gives a Bleſſing to thoſe, who, without any regular Call to it, impatiently leap out of that Rank, in which his Providence has ſeen fit to place them; but ſuch Perſons are commonly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunate,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:63795:20"/>
and very rarely ſuffered to be ſucceſsfull. And accordingly it was the ſaying of <hi>Luther;</hi> That, <hi>He ſhould be very loath to be a Soldier in that Army, where Prieſts were Captains, becauſe the Church, and not the Camp, is their proper place; and going to War, they willingly outed themſelves, of God's Protection, being out of their own Vocation.</hi> To which I think, I may, with Parity of Reaſon, add, that I ſhould be no leſs loath to joyn my ſelf a Member of that Congregation, where the pretended Paſtor, was never any regularly Ordained Miniſter, but a meer Lay-Uſurper upon the ſacred Office, whether Soldier (as ſuch have been) or Tradeſman, or illiterate <hi>Mechanick.</hi> However, I am ſure, that one of the moſt Remarkable Judgments, that God ever yet inflicted, (for ought we read) ſince the World began, upon any Sinners, and ſuch as may well ſerve as a ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Warning-piece, to all other Perſons alike evilly inclined, was that old-new thing, which he created for the Puniſhment of ſuch, as only attempted to Uſurp upon that Holy Office; when that Arch-Buſybody <hi>Corah</hi> and his Pragmatical Company, were ſwallowed up quick by the Earth, commanded viſibly to cleave in ſunder for that Purpoſe. And though God does not think fit, to repeat the like dreadful Judgment, upon all Offenders of the like nature; yet ſuch is the uſual hazard and inſucceſsfulneſs of ſuch Perſons, that the Wiſe <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaw cauſe enough, therefrom, to ground that general Obſervation of his, with which I ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude this Particular, <hi>Prov.</hi> 27. 8. <hi>As a bird that wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dereth from her Neſt, ſo is a Man that wandereth from his place.</hi> That is, as the leſſer Birds cannot depart from their reſting places, without becoming Obnoxious to Nets and Snares, and the Fury of Birds of prey; ſo for a Man to keep cloſe to his own proper Station and
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:63795:21"/>
Calling, is always the ſafeſt for him, by forſaking of which he uſually expoſeth himſelf to many Dangers and Miſfortunes.</p>
            <p>But <hi>Fourthly,</hi> though ſuch Men do happen alſo to be ſucceſsful, yet they cannot do half ſo much good to the Publick, by their particular Succeſs, as they are ſure to do miſchief to it, by the ill Influence of their Pragmatical Examples. For if every Man himſelf may once be allowed to be the ſole judge of his own Parts and Abilities, there are few perſons (howſoever really ſtupid and uncapable) will be found to conceit ſo meanly of themſelves, as not preſently to think them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ſufficiently fit and qualified, for the undertaking almoſt of any Office or Employment. And 'twill be natural from the Examples of ſome other Succeſsful Buſybodys and Intruders, for every Man thus to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe within himſelf. Nature, I am ſure, has been no leſs bountiful to me, nor have I wanted as good Education and Opportunity of emproving my ſelf, as ſuch a perſon; and why may not I alſo therefore pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume of as good Succeſs? If ſuch a one, who never made it his Buſineſs, is fit to undertake ſuch an Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment, why am not I as well qualified for, or may not, by the ſame right and juſtice, attempt to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge his Office, or any other Perſon's, which I moſt Fancy?</p>
            <p>How natural it is for ſuch Pragmatical Examples, to have this ill Effect upon others, was wittily repreſented, in the ſharp Reproof of an imprudent Action of King <hi>Lewis</hi> the Eleventh of <hi>France;</hi> who having appointed a certain Biſhop, to take the general Muſter of Soldiers at <hi>Paris,</hi> and <hi>Chabannes,</hi> one of his Noblemen, taking this thing in ill part, deſired of the King to give him the
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:63795:21"/>
Authority of cenſuring the ſaid Biſhop's Clergy-men; to which the King replying, <hi>that it was not fit to put ones Sickle into another man's Corn;</hi> Yes, ſaith the other, ſince the Biſhop has made our Harveſt, his own; why may not we alſo as well make his, ours? Thus what can be of worſe Conſequence to a Commonwealth, than for men to have ſuch Occaſions of Encouragement, in that pragmatical reſtleſs Humour, which moſt are, of themſelves, but too much naturally prone to? And ſo, whilſt neglecting the Duties of their own proper pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, this man, who perhaps never had Capacity enough to learn, ſhall be prompted to ſet up for a Teacher and Inſtructer of others; and another man to turn Stateſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man and Magiſtrate, who never knew how to obey; and another intruding himſelf into another's Province, and ſo on: In a Word, whilſt all men will be every thing, and no man, at laſt, any thing he ſhould be; muſt not all be perfectly unfixt, by this means? or what elſe can enſue from hence, in this Caſe, but lamentable Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order, and the moſt abſolute Confuſion?</p>
            <p>But ſtill <hi>Fifthly,</hi> Were it not a thing of ſuch conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Damage, as it really is, to the Publick; yet ſuch pragmaticalneſs is, in it ſelf, a very great Sin, and ſuch as includes, in the very nature of it, many and grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous Vices; as being evidently made up of a certain Complication, of Diſcontent, Pride, Covetouſneſs, Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition, and Injuſtice; of the laſt of which eſpecially, it has apparently ſo large a Doſe, that ſeveral Moraliſts know not how more fitly to place it, than under the rank of a certain ſort of Injuſtice. And indeed, though it be not only juſt, but alſo an Act of Charity, for a man that is able, out of meer good will, to lend his helping hand to another, when his Advice and Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:63795:22"/>
is either needed or deſired, by the Perſon there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in concerned; and accordingly in this ſenſe, ſome have underſtood (I inquire not now how truly) that of the Apoſtle, as a Precept, to this purpoſe, Phil. 2. 4. <hi>That we ſhould not look only on our own things, but every man alſo on the things of others:</hi> yet what can be more highly diſparaging? what more contrary to the Rules both of Charity and Juſtice, than the pragmatical In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaſion of another man's Office, againſt his own Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, when our interpoſal in the Affair, is neither needed, nor deſired? nay, when we are neither able, nor willing to do the Perſon any Courteſie; but indeed directly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign the quite contrary, thereby? How far is this from doing, as we would be done by? or who would not take it grievouſly to be himſelf thus dealt with? And now, to put the caſe more home, and render it more uſeful, by giving ſuch a particular Inſtance, in which men are apt, both moſt commonly and injuriouſly to offend, in this kind; ſuppoſe then, that the King, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of his great Miniſters, vouchſafing to caſt an eye in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to any of your Shops, ſhould, upon any ſlight Hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſay or Information, preſently determine, that ſuch or ſuch a man (though he has all his life-time made it his Buſineſs) does not, in my Opinion, competently under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, nor is he fit to follow the Trade he does profeſs; I will therefore take care to chuſe his Journey-men or Partners for him, and put in ſome of mine own Follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, men of better Parts, to manage his Affairs for him; Suppoſe, I ſay, His Majeſty ſhould proceed with you after this manner; How patiently, do you think, you ſhould be able to take it? would you not all immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately complain of Tyranny and Arbitrary Government, and make the moſt heavy Out-cries, that your Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and Properties were invaded? And yet now, I
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:63795:22"/>
pray, turn the Scales a little; and conſider whether it be not far more hard and injurious, for any of you, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getting your own Shop-boards, ſawcily either by Words or in your Behaviour (ſo far as you dare) to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timate, That His Majeſty<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> does not ſufficiently under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand His Buſineſs; that either your ſelves, or ſuch a one, could Govern far better; that he is wholly lead a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide by Evil-Counſellers; and that you muſt endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to have ſuch and ſuch a Judge, ſuch a Privy Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellor, or Miniſter of State removed, or elſe nothing can ever go well? What intollerable Inſolence and Injuſtice is there is ſuch kind of Behaviour? How come you, I wonder, ſo inſpired to underſtand King-craft, far better than that Perſon himſelf who was born and bred to it, who has had all the Advantages of Nature, Education, long Experience, and the moſt ſingular Opportunities, to be an abſolute Maſter in his Royal Trade? Is this indeed to be look'd upon as a far leſs Myſtery, and ſuch as may more eaſily be learnt, than any of your inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our petty Crafts? or can you think it more tollerable and leſs injurious, for a Subject to uſurp upon the Prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatives of the Crown, than it would be for the Prince to intrench upon a private man's particular Calling? If all this be moſt ridiculous to imagine; then, for ſhame, mind your own Buſineſs, and let State Affairs alone to whom they properly belong, and ceaſe any more ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtly and prophanely to treat Majeſty. If you ſhould take it ſo ill, that any ſhould meddle in your Trades, or put your Journey-men, or Partners upon you; be then intreated, out of common Juſtice, to let your So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereign alſo manage the State, and give him leave ſolely to chuſe and keep, ſuch Miniſters and Aſſiſtants, as himſelf ſhall think beſt qualified for that purpoſe. In ſhort, however ſlight or innocent, general Cuſtom
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:63795:23"/>
and the Multitude of Offenders may have made this Vice eſteemed, by moſt men; we ſhall find, (if we will take St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s Judgment in the Caſe) that it is indeed to be look'd upon, as a Sin of the moſt heinous nature; inſomuch that this Apoſtle plainly ſuppoſeth, both that ſuch pragmatical Perſons well deſerve to ſuffer, and that, let their Puniſhment be never ſo ſevere, they are far e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough from ſuffering, as Chriſtians; Nay, he can afford to rank them with no better Company, than thoſe which they are indeed ſo near akin to, even with Thieves and Murderers, 1 Pet. 4. 15. <hi>But let none of you ſuffer as a Murderer, or as a Thief, or as an Evil-doer, or as a Buſie-body in other men's Matters.</hi> To conclude, we may alſo know what to think, both of the Guilt and Danger of all ſuch Perſons, if we well conſider the Grounds and Reaſons of that excellent Advice of the Son of <hi>Syrach,</hi> Eccluſ. 11. 10. <hi>My Son, meddle not with many Matters,</hi> (that is, not belonging to thee) <hi>for if thou meddle much, thou ſhalt not be innocent; and if thou follow after, thou ſhalt not obtain; neither ſhalt thou e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcape, by flying.</hi> That muſt needs be a great Sin, which is complicated of ſo many others, and by which we do ſo apparent Wrong, both to God, and man.</p>
            <p>Which would bring me now to the Sixth and laſt aggravating Conſideration of it, <hi>viz.</hi> That this Prag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matical Temper is highly injurious to the Divine Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence, and Government of the World; wholly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiſtent with all neceſſary Order, and directly tending to obſtruct the Peace and General Benefit of Mankind, and to introduce the utter Ruin and Diſſolution of all Humane Society. But indeed all this is in it ſelf, ſo very evident and notorious, that barely to name things, may be ſufficient; nor ſhall I therefore think it needful
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:63795:23"/>
to proceed to any more particular Demonſtration here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; eſpecially, ſince I before touched upon the ſame, under ſome of the former Heads.</p>
            <p>I ſhall therefore here only add, That as this wretched Temper, whereſoever it is ſuffered to prevail, is enough to turn the World upſide down, ſo we of this Nation have, by woful experience, been inſtructed concerning the moſt curſed<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Effects thereof; in thoſe horrid Diſorders and Confuſions, which have been wholly owing to thoſe among us, who call themſelves by the Name of Diſſenters. In whom this Pragmatical Temper is ſo No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toriouſly Predominant, that it ſeems to be as the very <hi>Evil Genius,</hi> with which they are poſſeſſed. For as their Guides and Leaders, are the moſt Scandalous Buſybodys and groſs Uſurpers, in the very Office and Employment, which they have profeſſedly taken upon themſelves; ſo do they likewiſe make it their very De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign and Trade, to infect all their Followers, with the ſame Humour; whilſt they teach them (as a main point of Godlineſs) to be continually Murmuring and Complaining, to quarrel and find fault with, to be Medling, and Endeavouring (as they call it) to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form every Thing, and Perſon, but (what alone they can, and ought to reform) themſelves: In ſhort, to be at every thing, beſides that alone in which they ſhould be really Concerned; and <hi>in whatſoever State they are,</hi> never <hi>to be therewith contented.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now my hearty Prayer to God, and earneſt Entreaty to all, and eſpecially to ſuch Perſons, is, that they would, at length, but diligently reflect upon what has been, and muſt neceſſarily be the ſad Effects and fatal Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequences of this Curſed Temper; that they would ſeriouſly conſider what has now been ſaid concerning it; How ſuch Buſybodies in other Mens matters muſt
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:63795:24"/>
neceſſarily neglect their own proper Buſineſs, by the due following of which they might be moſt happy here; and for the Neglect of which, they are ſure to be ſo ſadly accountable hereafter; that they meddle with what they cannot, ordinarily, underſtand, nor are any way fitly qualified to manage; that if they did competently un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the ſame, yet Providence ſeldom ſuffers ſuch Intruders to be ſucceſsfull in what they undertake; that though they ſhould happen to be Succeſsful, yet their particular Succeſs never does the Publick half ſo much good, as they are ſure to do it Miſchief, by the ill Influence of their Pragmatical Examples; that this Pragmaticalneſs is in it ſelf ſo great a Sin, and Complicated of ſo many other grievous Vices; that it ſo highly affronts the Divine Providence, and ſo directly diſturbs the Order, Peace and Quietneſs of the World.</p>
            <p>If theſe men, I ſay, who<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> talk ſo much of Conſcience, and pretend ſo great Scrupulouſneſs, where they need not, would but, in earneſt, conſider the great Sin, which they are, hereby guilty of, and all theſe, and many more Miſchiefs, which they incur themſelves, and bring upon others, by ſuch their reſtleſs and pragmatical Behaviour; they would then ſee ſufficient reaſon, to mind and med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle with their own Buſineſs only; and ſo, better find in their hearts, <hi>To ſtudy to be quiet,</hi> and to ſuffer others alſo, that are about them, to be ſo. Then, might we, indeed, hope for true, and laſting Peace and Proſperity; whilſt, Living together like Fellow-Citizens, like Brethren and Chriſtians, we ſhould all, in our ſeveral proper Places, make it our Buſineſs mutually <hi>to ſerve each other in Love,</hi> and Bleſſed Concord. O, well would it then be with us, and happy ſhould we be!</p>
            <p>Thus having competently finiſhed the main things which I deſigned from this Text, there is now no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:63795:24"/>
elſe remaining, but ſome more particular Appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation. Which, I think, will moſt naturally be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, by endeavouring chiefly to Anſwer ſuch com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Objections, as I know many will be ready to make, againſt my Diſcourſe in General upon this Subject. What I ſhall ſay, (I muſt tell them before hand) will chiefly Concern, and muſt therefore be Underſtood, as more particularly directed to Diſſenters, or their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed Favourers. With whom I am reſolved (let them take it how they will) to deal with all imaginable Plainneſs and Freedom. And indeed, if it be not now high time to do ſo, (and that, not without ſome Hopes too of better Succeſs, than formerly) their Diſeaſe muſt be altogether deſperate and incurable; and I know not when this charitable Office either will, or can be ſeaſonable. And yet I cannot chuſe but be heartily troubled for their ſakes, to obſerve; how highly they are ſtill Enraged and Offended, at all Diſcourſes of this Nature. For what then? Are they ſtill even at this time of day, ſo much Enemies unto Peace and Quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, that they cannot endure to hear a Man ſpeak to them thereof, but they muſt be ready to fly in his Face, and preſently prepare themſelves for Battel? I ſhould have thought truly, that after they and their Friends, had ſo long, and ſo much both Said and Written, Acted and Contrived, in order to the ſetting this Kingdom in a Flame, and to the utter Ruin of the preſent Government, that we, who were deſigned by them as Sheep to the Slaughter, might now <hi>at length,</hi> after the ſo plain Diſcovery and Defeat of their Malice, have had the Liberty, at leaſt, to have told them of their Bloody-Mindedneſs, and to endeavour (if poſſible) to perſwade them to Repentance.</p>
            <p>But does not this kind of Behaviour indeed Argue in
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:63795:25"/>
them, the moſt Deſperately Malicious, obſtinate Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, and that they are ſtill ſo far from any Real Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trition, or the leaſt thoughts of Reformation, that they have ſtill as much Mind, as ever, to be carrying on their Accurſed Plots, and cannot therefore endure, that what they have already done, ſhould be ſpoken of or believed, for fear it ſhould hinder them of being Succeſsful, in what they are ready to deſign farther, upon the firſt Opportunity? That Charity muſt firſt put out its own Eyes, that can make any more favourable Conſtruction, of their ſo exceſſive Rage and Impatience, upon theſe Occaſions.</p>
            <p>But yet as for mine own part, I confeſs I have not ſo much reaſon to complain, as having hitherto (God be praiſed) fared better than ſome other of my Brethren, who, perhaps, have not been more plain with their Party, than my ſelf neither. For ſeveral Miniſters, even ſince the Diſcovery of the Phanatical Conſpiracy, have been Deſperately threatned, and it is well known, how one Reverend Divine was, not long ſince, knock't down in the open Streets, and Miſerably Bruiſed and Battered, to the no ſmall hazard of his Life, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the Endeavours of ſeveral good People to reſcue him; and all this, at the ſame time expreſly ſignified, by the Ruffian himſelf, to have been done for no other cauſe, but only his Loyalty, and that he had ſhewn himſelf againſt the Deſigns of the Diſſenters.</p>
            <p>Now if this ſort of Men can afford to ſhew themſelves ſuch fell Creatures, even whilſt the Law and Civil Power is againſt them, and their hands are pretty well tyed up; then Judge, I pray, what abſolute Tigers and Dragons they muſt needs prove, were they but once looſe, and had all (as they deſire) under their own Dominion? what could we elſe expect, but to be
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:63795:25"/>
all flea'd alive, and to be torn by them (like the Arch-Biſhop of St. <hi>Andrews</hi>) into a hundred pieces? And yet a man cannot open his mouth, to give good Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple warning, nor ſpeak the leaſt word, of the horrid Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices or Principles of theſe men, but preſently ſome or other of their Favourers are ready to ſtand up for them, and ſlander it, under the odious Name of (that which is indeed their general Character of all ſuch charitable Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofs) down right Railing and Reviling.</p>
            <p>And, <hi>What</hi> (ſay ſome) <hi>ſhould we go to Church for? We ſhould go thither to profit; but truly we cannot bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit at all, by ſuch kind of Preaching.</hi> Can they not ſo, indeed? I am heartily ſorry to hear it. But what is the reaſon that they cannot benefit? I doubt the fault will be no bodies, but their own; and I fear they'll hardly ever believe themſelves to benefit, by any Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, but only ſuch as really tends (if poſſible) to make them worſe than they are already, by ſtill more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firming them, in their wretched Errours and Iniquities. But I would fain know what ſuch men mean, by their not benefitting. If they were but rightly ſenſible of their own meaning, I am perſwaded they can under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand nothing elſe, by it, but that they are not at all pleaſed, with what they hear. And it is very grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous to them, to be told of, or to think of amending their Faults. As for my own part, I am not conſcious to my ſelf, that, in what has been now ſaid, I have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered any thing, but the Words of Truth and Sober<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. And if Truth, plain Scripture, and Reaſon will not go down with them, I know not how to help it; they are not indeed ſo much offended with <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s,</hi> in theſe Caſes, as (in effect) with Chriſt himſelf, and the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of his Apoſtles. And there is no other Remedy, but they muſt e'en go ſeek out for ſome other Goſpel,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:63795:26"/>
that will better agree with their corrupt Luſts, that they may profit by the hearing of it: for as for that of our bleſſed Saviour, whilſt they reſolve to continue thus affected, it will never be able to do the feat for them.</p>
            <p>But if ſuch men do indeed believe the Scripture, and are willing equally to be guided by it, as their Rule in all things; coming to theſe places with an honeſt teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able heart, ready to forſake their Errours, and to do their Duty, whenſoever they ſhall be made ſenſible thereof; then (I can aſſure them) that ſuch kind of Preaching will highly both pleaſe and profit them; far more, perhaps, than all the Sermons put together, which ever they heard in Conventicles, their whole life-time. By which, I fear, they have profited hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to only backward, and the wrong way; whilſt this kind of Preaching, if practiſed, will indeed benefit them, even to the ſaving of their Souls; which are now ſo imminently hazarded, by their woful Diſobedience and horrid Contempt of the Laws both of God and Man.</p>
            <p>But again, (as ſome will object) is this the way to bring in Diſſenters, to be thus continually inveighing againſt them? Nay, is it not rather the ready way to drive thoſe out again, who are already a comming in?</p>
            <p>In anſwer to which, I ſhall Firſt conſider, how the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerality of thoſe, who have yet made any Approaches at all, have hitherto ſhewed themſelves a coming in to us.</p>
            <p>Some, 'tis true, have come hither, and received the Holy Sacrament with us; but (as themſelves have given too juſt Occaſion to fear) meerly to ſerve a Turn, or to qualifie them for ſome Place, in which they
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:63795:26"/>
might have an Opportunity of doing the Church and State ſo much the more Miſchief: for they have received no more, nor ſcarce ever came to Church again, for a whole twelve Month afterwards.</p>
            <p>Others again, awakened by the fear of Legal Penal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, have received here in the Morning, and (as I am credibly informed) in the Afternoon, in a Conventicle; as if they meant preſently there to undo again, what they had here done; or deſigned to make that which ſhould be the Bond of Chriſtian Charity, ſerve only more to confirm them in their Schiſm, and moſt ſinful Separation.</p>
            <p>And their deceitful Guides (I find) have furniſhed them, with that more than Jeſuitical Diſtinction, of a Legal and a Neceſſary Receiving. The firſt of which with us, ſtands for juſt nothing, but meerly to ſatisfie the Law; whilſt the ſecond with them, is that only which is to be accounted real and effectual.</p>
            <p>Others there are who come hither uſually, when Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Service is either quite, or almoſt done: and then ſitting too all the remainder of it, as if they ſcorned ſo much as to ſeem to joyn with us therein; and we have not wanted Inſtances of running out again in a fury, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Sermon was at an end.</p>
            <p>In ſhort, too many of them (for I charge not all) have hitherto ſo lamely and awkwardly joyned with us, and after ſuch a manner, as would tempt one to think they ſtudied to have us believe, that they only play'd the Hypocrites in ſo doing.</p>
            <p>Nor let any one ſay, this is an unwarrantable judging of other men's Hearts; for we may ſafely, and without breach of Charity, judge of men's hearts, from the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor of their Actions and Behaviour.</p>
            <p>And beſides, ſome of them have been ſo very ſilly and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:63795:27"/>
ſhameleſs, as openly to declare and profeſs, <hi>that they would come to Church, only once a Month, or ſo, to avoid the Laſh of the Law, not out of any ſenſe of Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</hi> Whereas, by the way, let me tell ſuch, that they may find, this will not be enough to ſatisfie the Law neither, any more than it ought to ſatisfie their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience.</p>
            <p>This now has been (for the generality) the main of their coming in, which I have been yet able to take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of. But ſuppoſe, that, now at length, they were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed diſpoſed, in more good earneſt to joyn with us; why ſhould ſuch Diſcourſes of Peace and Quietneſs, of Loyalty and Obedience, and plainly to mind them, wherein they have been hitherto notoriouſly guilty of the Breach of theſe Duties, Why ſhould this, I ſay, ſo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently again fright them away from us? If they are reſolved to become real Converts, how is it poſſible they ſhould be ſo very nice and ſqueamiſh? for how can they ever ſo truly repent, unleſs they be firſt made tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowly ſenſible of their Errors? or how ſhould they be ſo ſenſible of them, unleſs they be plainly told of them? or where can they expect this plain dealing, if not in theſe Places? Methinks, after they have been ſo long uſed to be ſoothed up, flattered and confirmed in their wicked Follies, were they but now really diſpoſed to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards any Reformation of them, they might be well enough contented, for once in their lives, to be roundly told their own.</p>
            <p>But if their Deſign be, ſo only to come hither and joyn with us, as yet to bring with them and ſtill keep all their former Pride, Prejudice, implacable Malice, and ſeditious Principles; I muſt needs tell them, that our Church will never be large enough long to hold them; and their <hi>Room</hi> will be here more acceptable than their <hi>Company.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:63795:27"/>For if it be ſufficient only to bring men's Bodies hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, without their Minds; we needed not then to be ſo very ſolicitous about this Matter. 'Tis but ſtaying a little while, and Death will ſoon do this Feat for us. That will ere long, not fail to bring in all Diſſenters, to the Church or the Church-yard. Their Carcaſſes will then conform, and lie peaceable enough here with ours, nor will they ſcruple to mingle Aſhes with thoſe of them, who have been the higheſt for the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But in the mean time, our main Buſineſs is ſo to bring them in hither, that our Souls may be united; to reform their Minds, and perſwade them to lay aſide thoſe unruly Luſts and evil Principles that have ſo long poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt them; and this they will never do, till they can firſt patiently bear Reproof: and yet, till this be indeed done, come here as often as they will, Light and Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs may aſſoon be reconciled, as they and we be really united.</p>
            <p>In ſhort, If they ſtill deſire to be flattered, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve never to have their Conſciences thorowly awake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, by hearing of thoſe Sins, of which they are moſt guilty; Our Churches, I hope, will be no convenient Places for them. There is no remedy, but they muſt e'en return (if they can) to their Old Meeting-houſes again; where it is the proper Work and Buſineſs, the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Profeſſion of the Maſters of thoſe Aſſemblies, to lull men aſleep, and moſt induſtriouſly to train them up, and confirm them, in their moſt pernicious Errors: Their moſt notorious Sins are both the Food and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creation of thoſe Paſtors; who <hi>eat up the Sin of the People,</hi> are maintained, and grow rich by their damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Separation. Theſe Guides will be ſure to flatter and pleaſe them, in their Luſts, that they may be followed
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:63795:28"/>
and admired of them, and themſelves profit thereby. There indeed, ſuch will never be reminded, of their Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Pride, Malice, or Hatred; nor yet of their Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quietneſs and Pragmaticalneſs; of their Lies, Slanders, or moſt horrid Perjuries; nor of any other of thoſe moſt unſociable Vices, which make them become no ſmall Plague, both to themſelves and the whole Nation. They may indeed continue long enough, in thoſe Places, and never hear ſo much as one word of thoſe grievous Faults of theirs, till they come at laſt to hear of them, at the day of Judgment.</p>
            <p>But as for the Buſineſs of thoſe faithful Miniſters, who would indeed preach Chriſt Jeſus, and not them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, it is of a quite oppoſite Nature and Deſign. Theſe are, and always will be ſo determined, as that they had much rather (if it cannot be otherwiſe) by their plain-dealing, and telling men neceſſary Truths, affright away ſuch obſtinate and incorrigible Offenders, than by a cowardly ſilence, in theſe Points, be fawned upon and crowded after (as ſome are) by never ſo great Multitudes of Hypocrites of all ſorts. Nor will they ever change their Minds, or forbear, ſometimes, to tell ſuch men roundly of their Faults, till ſuch time as they give ſome better and more ſubſtantial Arguments, than yet they have done, of their Repentance and Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Let us but once ſee this happy Day, and then we'll all lay our Hands upon our Mouths; they ſhall never hear one word more of their former Behaviour: but all that is already paſt, ſhall, by my conſent, be buried in eternal Silence and Oblivion. For, as for my own part, whatſoever ſome may think, I can aſſure them, that it is, in it ſelf, no ſuch grateful Office to me, to be ripping up ſore places. Nothing in the World puts me upon this Employment, but the real ſenſe of my
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:63795:28"/>
Duty herein, joyned with the moſt unfeigned Charity towards the Souls of the Perſons ſo much concerned. For, if I have any acquaintance with my own Heart, I think I could be contented to part with the laſt drop of blood therein, might I but thereby ſecure the ſpiritual Welfare of any the worſt Enemy I have, or can have a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them.</p>
            <p>But whilſt they continue to excuſe, or deny the late notorious Crimes of their Party; whilſt they endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to make Martyrs, of thoſe who have juſtly ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for their moſt damnable Treaſon; and go about to defend them as innocent, in ſpite of their own plain Confeſſions, and the moſt Sun-beam Evidences to the contrary: In a Word, whilſt they cannot ſo much as endure to hear of this Matter; I muſt needs tell them, that theſe are no ſuch excellent Signs of their Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.</p>
            <p>But to this, perhaps, ſome may be ready to object; <hi>What are we concerned in theſe things? or why do you tell us of Repenting? For, certainly, you do not take any of us to have been in the late Plot; do you?</hi> Truly, no, I do not, perhaps, believe them to be ſo guilty of it, as that the Law can take hold of them: But yet, (to deal freely with them) I cannot but think the whole Body of Diſſenters, to have been in the general more or leſs, concerned therein; Nor do I believe any tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row-paced Conventicler of them all, ſo wholly inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent in this caſe, before God, but that they have great need to repent. For, if they had either Eyes or Ears, they could not but be ſenſible, in the general, of a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign on foot, among thoſe of their own Party, for the Deſtruction of the preſent Government. It is next to impoſſible that they ſhould go conſtantly to Conven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles, and yet be ignorant of thus much.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:63795:29"/>Nor do I ſpeak this raſhly, and without ſufficient Grounds: For, what will you ſay, If I give you ſome evident Demonſtrations, even from their own late Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, both that the Phanatical Preachers were not igno<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rant of the late horrid Conſpiracy, and that they have alſo, all along, for ſeveral Years together in their Publick Preachments, made it their Buſineſs, not only plainly enough to ſignifie the ſame, but alſo to inſtigate and prepare their ſeveral Congregations to do the bloody work of it?</p>
            <p>Will they not then believe there was a Plot, when they hear it, even from their Teachers own Mouths? I hope they do not know them to be ſuch notorious Lyars, but that they will believe what they ſpeak from the very Pulpit. And though I confeſs, indeed, that or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily (to uſe the Pſalmiſt's Phraſe) <hi>Their very Preaching is of Curſing and Lies;</hi> yet I know no Reaſon why they ſhould not be credited, in this Caſe.</p>
            <p>Now what I have propoſed, I make no queſtion, but that I ſhall be able eaſily to make out, to the full ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of all, excepting only ſuch as indeed need no Conviction in the Caſe, and will therefore never ſeem to believe, becauſe they full well know the thing alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to be moſt true, and themſelves alſo deeply engaged therein. All others, I doubt not, that have any Eyes, I ſhall ſoon enlighten, by the help of ſome certain Jew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els; which, (though, I ſuppoſe, not very eaſie to be had, as being deſigned only for the particular Comfort and Edification of the Saints; yet) hap'ned, by good fortune, to ſtragle into my hands. The firſt, of which I ſhall now make uſe, and ſhew you ſome Rays, has this Title or Inſcription; <hi>A moſt uſeful Sermon, Preached in</hi> London, <hi>one Faſt-day, in the Year, 1670. By a moſt faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Miniſter of Chriſt, for the Support and Comfort of
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:63795:29"/>
the People of God, in evil Times, opened and preſſed from Pſ. 91. 11. Light is ſown for the Righteous, and Printed in the Year,</hi> 1676. For, or by whom, they durſt not ſet. Now in this Diſcourſe, <hi>pag.</hi> 35. there is this Inference, which you muſt be content to take, as all the reſt, in his own Words.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>If Light and Comfort be ſown for the Righteous; Why, then here is Comfort this Day, for the Church of God in</hi> England; <hi>the Seed is in the Ground, and Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, in God's due ſeaſon, ſhall ſpring up, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then follows ſome Lines after; <hi>I confeſs things here amongst us, as they have a ſad Aſpect this Day, I would be ſenſible of your Condition. If we are not ſenſible of God's hand, we cannot be humbled under it. I would be ſenſible of it, grey hairs are here and there; ſad Symptoms of God's Diſpleaſure are upon us; our Sins grow higher, and our Trading grows lower, &amp;c. Yet, I ſay, in this Day of Mourning, I would not have you mourn, as they without Hope. My Text tells you, that Light is ſown for the Righteous. There is a little Light, God knows, it is but very little Light; we can ſcarce ſee it at the Key-hole; but there is ſome Light ſown for the Righteous. There are three Seeds of Comfort, for this poor dying ſelf-deſtroying Nation. First, God hath a People in this Land that fears him</hi> (he means, you may be ſure, the Diſſenters) <hi>and are very dear to him; that is one Seed of Comfort; they are to him, as the Apple of his Eye, they are the Glory of Christ; they are God's Jewels, all the rest of the World are but Lumber.</hi> (Wonderful Charity and Humility!) <hi>God hath a Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple dear to him in</hi> England. <hi>Were the Godly removed, as it is the deſire of ſome to give them their Paſs, to be gone; Why, God would ſoon make quick work with the Nation; He would ſoon break up Houſe in</hi> England, <hi>were it not
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:63795:30"/>
for the Elect, he would ſoon ſink Ship and State; but for ſome Elect Jewels in the Ship, but for their ſakes, the Lord may reprieve the Nation.</hi> Then, after ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of his Comforts, he comes in the 41. <hi>pag.</hi> to this Caution; <hi>But here I muſt inſert a Caution. And I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you to obſerve; Though there be ſome Light ſown for the Righteous, yet take this Caution; Expect an hour of Darkneſs. It is uſually dark before Morning. Things are like to be worſe with us, before they are better. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Goſpel-deliverance you must expect ſome ſore Pangs; and the reaſon of it is this</hi> (and let me beſeeeh you to mind his Reaſon) <hi>here is the Reaſon; becauſe God has a great deal of work yet to do; there is much Rubbiſh to be removed</hi> (you know his meaning, for he told you before, that all are Lumber and Rubbiſh but themſelves) <hi>much Rubbiſh to be removed, before God's Spiritual Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple will be built; Sins muſt be brought lower; Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition muſt be purged away; the Devil muſt be caſt out; and will not this, think you, cauſe great Commotion in the Church, and Convulſion fits, before Light ſpring up? therefore look for an hour of Darkneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The moſt Prophetick man, it ſeems, could foreſee; that we wicked ſuperſtitious Wretches, when the Saints ſhould come to attaque us, would not ſtand ſtill, and tamely ſuffer them to cut our Throats and ſwallow all, without making ſome Buſle and Reſiſtance. Then he concludes in the 47. <hi>pag.</hi> with an Encouragement, in theſe Words; <hi>The Mercies we are in expectation of, they are worthy waiting for; The Mercies we have pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for, and are in expectation of, they are worthy waiting for; To ſee the Golden Fleet of Prayer coming home, with rich Returns; Is not that worth waiting for? To ſee the Lilly and the Roſe <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited, I mean Truth and Peace; To ſee Wickedneſs diſcountenanced, and all its
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:63795:30"/>
Forces disbanded; To ſee the Beauty of Holineſs ſhin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in our Chriſtal, to ſee Jeſus Chriſt riding in Triumph, in his Chariots of Goſpel-adminiſtration,</hi> &amp;c. Now is it not pretty plain, from all this ſtuff, that they had long ago, ſome hopes of ſwallowing Biſhops lands again, and getting all into their own hands.</p>
            <p>But this, you muſt know, was a great while ago, and this Man ſaw Light <hi>only through the Key-hole;</hi> and yet, not ſo much the time of his Preaching, but the time of Printing this Sermon, is chiefly to be taken notice of; and this was in the year—76. And even then you muſt alſo conſider, that 'twas but early Days with them; much about the time (if I miſtake not) when <hi>Marvel</hi>'s <hi>Growth of Popery</hi> came out; and then the Maſters of this fellow were but juſt framing of <hi>their</hi> Popiſh Plot, (for <hi>theirs,</hi> I ſhall not ſtick to call all falſe Additions to the Real one) for the ſetting up of Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naticiſm, and the Deſtruction of the preſent Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; then their among all, other <hi>ſeeds of Comfort,</hi> their Wild Oats were but juſt a Sowing; or, at moſt, lay only a Corrupting; the Blade had not yet appeared above Ground.</p>
            <p>But all this is juſt nothing, in reſpect of what we may find in another of their Sermons, which I have by me, bearing this Title; England's <hi>condition Parallel'd, in a Sermon, Preached by a Servant of the Lord's, learnedly Opened and Preſſed from</hi> Jer. 30. 7. London, <hi>Printed for</hi> J. Johnſon, <hi>in the Year</hi> 1682.</p>
            <p>Then their Plot was almoſt Hanging-ripe, and you ſhall hear how boldly this Man ſpeaks, as if they had concluded, that all was abſolutely their own. I ſhall need but barely to repeat ſome paſſages, without making any Reflections, but leave you to be judges in the Caſe.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:63795:31"/>And <hi>First,</hi> it is Remarkable, how ſadly he Alarmes his People with Fears and Jealouſies, <hi>P.</hi> 11. in theſe Words; <hi>I do ſay that the Churches of God, may meet with Land-wasting, Houſes-burning, Women-raviſhing, Child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>killing, State-devouring, Religion-ſcorning, Ordinances<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſting-down, Heart-trembling, and Liberties-over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwing-times.</hi> And I readily confeſs, for my part, ſo they may, and will, if theſe Men come once again to prevail. But <hi>P.</hi> 19. he comes moſt directly to his Buſineſs. <hi>Let me tell you, my dear Friends, That, upon four Occaſions, times will be Troublous. Firſt, When Dagon and Baal is to go down. No great or prevailing Evil can be caſt down, without much Trouble and Tumult. If</hi> Gideon <hi>cast down the Altar of Baal, and cut down the Grove by it, the Men of the City keep a mighty ſtir about it. If the Goddeſs</hi> Diana <hi>be in danger, what a Noiſe and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>proar is there in the City! And I further conceive thus much; That</hi> England <hi>hath many bad<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants, who have gotten Poſſeſſion, and can plead Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription, tho no Scripture-Title for themſelves, yet they are reſolved not to go out, without great Trouble; neither can it be imagined, unleſs a Miracle be wrought by God, that ſo many Proud, droniſh Ministers; ſo many idle ſcandalous Non-reſidents; and ſo much Rubbiſh of humane Invention, as are crept into God's Worſhip, will ever be cast down, or carried out, without Troubles. Can you conceive that Satan will loſe his Kingdom, and never wag his tail! Believe it Brethren, There are many thouſands in the Kingdom ſo ſet upon Idolatry, Superſtition, and ways of Formality, that they cannot be quiet, if theſe things be taken from them. When the Temple is to be re-edified, no great and good Work can be carryed on, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out much Trouble. This is certain, God hath brought us to Church-reforming-times, and theſe always have been troubleſome times.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:63795:31"/>After this, he proceeds to give them a great many other reaſons why the times muſt be troubleſome, whereas, he might indeed have made ſhorter work, and included all under that, with which he did begin; For the times muſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> be Troubleſome, becauſe theſe Men are reſolved to make them ſo; nor can they, indeed, ever be otherwiſe, as long as their Seditious Conven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles are ſuffered, and ſuch vile Wretches as himſelf there permitted, to Poiſon and Seduce the poor ſilly Vulgar. But ſtill, afterwards he falls to encourage them again to the Work, by reminding them of their former Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs. <hi>P. 27. Had we not had our troublous times, we had not ſeen ſo many Wicked Men caſt down among us. What times have more diſcountenanced Enemies? What times have more diſcovered Enemies? What times have more croſt Enemies! Nay, what times have been more Deſtructive to Enemies, than the times of the Churches Troubles? Theſe Winds blow them no good. They always preſage their down-fall. And, for my own part, I do verily believe, that all the Troubles in</hi> England, <hi>will end in the Shame and Confuſion, of many Powerful and Politick Enemies,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Out of the moſt troubled womb came there greateſt quiet: If there were no War, there would be no Victory; though troubles Create not Mercy, yet they Occaſion and Ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cede. I am verily perſwaded, that</hi> England, <hi>which is now in great Troubles, is big with Child of ſome extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Mercy. We may not think, that theſe troubles ſhall end without a Bleſſing; let the Conſideration of theſe things ſtay your thoughts,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>In the ſelf-ſame Page likewiſe he cannot refrain from reviling, and endeavouring to render both the King himſelf, and all his Miniſters both in Church and State, Odious to the People. <hi>Have we not amongst us</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>all Land-wasting, did Land-weakening ſins. Most
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:63795:32"/>
of our Paſtors are either ignorant and Blind, or Corrupt, or unſound, ſo far from reforming themſelves, that they are Enemies to the much deſired Reformation.</hi> (That is, we would hinder People, from Rebelling again as much as we can,) <hi>Many of our Rulers and great Ones, are Idolaters, Adulterous, full of Pride and Idleneſs, leading many thouſands into Wickedneſs, by their evil Examples, following the Footsteps of</hi> Jeroboam, <hi>who made</hi> Iſrael <hi>to Sin. And, O, how many Times-troubling Enemies have we Lodging and Lurking among us; Men of no Religion, Men of a falſe Religion, a great Popiſh Party, Men of no Rank and Quality; whoſe Mouths are full of Scoffs and their hands full of Blood,</hi> (now he is at the Kings Gaurds) <hi>whoſe hope only lies in this; that ſhortly they ſhall raviſh our Virgins, Deflower our Wives, cut our Throats, and divide our Estates. What meaneth the Countenancing and Maintaining thoſe Vermin and Off<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcouring of the Land, but that troubleſome times are at hand? Certainly the Kingdom cannot vomit out theſe Frogs, or quit it ſelf of theſe Locusts, without much ado.</hi> (It ſeems they were reſolved to have the Guards down then.) I ſhall trouble you but with one paſſage more. <hi>P. 43. We must deſire and further a National Reformation; there must be a Purging of the Church from its Droſs, and there must be a ſetting up the Power and Purity of Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances. Every Man must ſtrive to reform and amend, or elſe the Kingdom (its greatly to be feared,) will fall aſunder. And we muſt cast out the endangering Enemies of the Kingdom. If you ſhall ſuffer</hi> (did he Preach to the <hi>Oxford</hi> Houſe of Commons, I Wonder, or to his own People?) <hi>If you ſhall ſuffer Men of Cruelty, Enemies to God and Religion, and not do justice upon them, the Kingdom cannot but be ruined.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now, for the upſhot of all, becauſe this Man's own
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:63795:32"/>
Conſcience could not but accuſe him, as Guilty of the moſt horrid Treaſon and Sedition, that he may clearly wipe off this Imputation, he tacitly ſuppoſeth himſelf immediatly inſpired of God, to ſay and do all this Villany; and therefore for a Concluſion, you muſt take his own bare Word for it, that <hi>they</hi> only who would hinder themſelves from putting all this in Execution, are to be look't upon, as the Make-bates and Incendiaries of the Nation, whereas he, and thoſe of his Party, are, notwithſtanding all this, no more the real Troublers of our <hi>Iſrael, than holy</hi> Elias, <hi>was.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I might have tranſcribed much more, both out of theſe, and out of ſeveral other late Diſcourſes of theirs, to the ſame purpoſe; but it is high time to have done; ſince this, I think, may be enough, in all reaſon.</p>
            <p>And truly, I hope, that none of you will be angry at me, for this way of Proceeding, or ſay that I might be aſhamed, to bring ſuch ſtuff as this is into the <hi>Pulpit,</hi> when you conſider, that it was there once before, or otherwiſe, you had not had it here now. For ought I know, ſome here preſent, may have beard the ſame at the Fountain's head, and if any of you did ſo, I make no Queſtion, but that you then thought your ſelves to profit, and were indeed wonderfully pleaſed therewith. And truly I ſee <hi>no Reaſon,</hi> why you may not (unleſs it be your own fault) more truly benefit by it now, thus at the ſecond hand; eſpecially ſince you uſe to be ſo much for Repetitions. You will not ſuſpect, I hope, that I have made this for them; for fear you ſhould thereby allow any of us able to Preach, ſo exceeding well as this comes to; for it has their own infallible Stamp and Shibboleth upon it; and beſides, I have their own Authentick Printed Copys by me, and much
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:63795:33"/>
more of the like Nature, at forth-coming for any that ſhall herein deſire ſatisfaction. And I beg their pardon only, that I have been forced a little to diſgrace the Matter for want of the right Twang and elegant<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Tone, the peculiar ſet-off, by which, uſually, ſuch Diſcourſes are chiefly<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> recommended to <hi>that ſober Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But however, as for all thoſe who would indeed de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve this Name (and to ſuch chiefly I ſhall now direct the ſmall Remainder of what I have to ſay) they may, I think, (had they no other Evidence) ſufficiently diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover from what they have now heard, what kind of Trade it is, that they drive, at Conventicles; and how impoſſible it is, for thoſe that have their Hearts ſet ſo upon going to thoſe Places, not to be utterly intoxica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and deſtroyed, by ſuch deadly Poyſon. They therefore who have any due Care either of their Souls or Bodies, may ſee, if they will, what they are to ſhun, as they would avoid a Peſt-houſe, or coming into the moſt dangerous Places of Infection. And you may eaſily enough judge, by this time, with whom you have moſt reaſon to be diſpleaſed; whether with thoſe who ſincerely Preach to you, the ever bleſſed and moſt peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Goſpel of our Saviour, or with them who have coin'd and would intrude upon you another, of their own, in direct oppoſition to it; whether with them, who make it their Buſineſs to exhauſt your Pockets, and corrupt your Minds; or with thoſe, who endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to rectifie your Underſtandings, and to cure your Luſts, deſiring no other temporal Reward, for the ſame, but that ſtanding Maintenance which the Law allows them; whether with them, who contrive all they can, to inſtigate you to thoſe horrid crying Sins of Murder, Rapine, and Rebellion, and would involve you, and
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:63795:33"/>
your Countrey, in endleſs Miſery and Confuſion, or with them, who do their beſt to hinder you from the Guilt of theſe heinous Crimes, and to ſecure you from all theſe dreadful Miſchiefs.</p>
            <p>In a Word, Remember to what ſad and ſhameful Ends the accurſed Doctrines of theſe men have already late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly brought ſo many<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> of their profeſſed Admirers; and conſider with your ſelves which of the two are really your beſt Friends; they, who ſincerely endeavour to ſecure your Necks here, and your Souls hereafter; or they, who direct you the ready way, to deſtroy both<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Chuſe your Friends, and then follow them. And if you do indeed believe this to be any part of the New Teſtament, and Word of Life, be then entreated, as you tender your everlaſting Welfare, (let others do what they pleaſe) to betake your ſelves to the <hi>Study of being Quiet, and to do your own Buſineſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>To which, that we may all, at length, moſt ſeriouſly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply our ſelves, the God of all Peace and Love, of his infinite Mercy Grant, through Jeſus Christ our Lord, to whom, &amp;c.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:63795:34"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:63795:34"/>
            <head>Books Printed for and ſold by <hi>Henry Bonwick,</hi> at the Red-Lyon in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-Yard.</head>
            <p>A Late Voyage to <hi>Conſtantinople:</hi> Containing an exact Deſcription of the <hi>Propontis</hi> and <hi>Helleſpont,</hi> with the <hi>Dardanels,</hi> and what is elſe Remarkable in thoſe Seas; as alſo of the City of <hi>Constantinople,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in is particularly deſcribed the Grand <hi>Seraglio</hi> and Chief <hi>Moſquees.</hi> Likewiſe an account of the ancient and preſent State of the <hi>Greek</hi> Church; with the Religion<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and manner of Worſhip of the <hi>Turks,</hi> their Eccleſiaſtical<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Government, their Courts of Juſtice, and civil Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments, Illuſtrated with Curious and Exact Draughts<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> of the <hi>Helleſpont, Propontis, Constantinople,</hi> the <hi>Sera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glio, Sancta Sophia,</hi> and other Chief <hi>Moſquees,</hi> with<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the ſeveral poſtures of the <hi>Turks</hi> during Prayer-time, in fourteen Copper-plates, the exactneſs whereof is atteſted by ſeveral Famous Travellers, publiſhed by Command of the <hi>French</hi> King, by Monſieur <hi>William Joſeph Grelot,</hi> made <hi>Engliſh</hi> by <hi>J. Phillips.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Certain Miſcellany Tracts, Written by <hi>Thomas Brown,</hi> Knight, and Doctor of Phyſick, late of <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wich.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Hiſtory of the late War with the <hi>Turks,</hi> during the Siege of <hi>Vienna,</hi> and the great Victory obtained againſt them, at the raiſing the Siege; together with
<pb facs="tcp:63795:35"/>
the under-hand dealings of <hi>France</hi> in that Affair, being the beſt and fulleſt Relation that has been yet Publiſhed, Printed at <hi>Cologn,</hi> and reprinted at <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Conſtant Communicant, a Diatribe, proving that Conſtancy in receiving the Lords Supper, is the indiſpenſable duty of every Chriſtian, the ſecond Edition, to which is added a Sermon Preached at the Anniverſary meeting of the Sons of Clergy-Men, at St. <hi>Mary le Bow,</hi> on the ſeventh of <hi>December,</hi> 1682. By <hi>Ar. Bury</hi> D. D. Rector of <hi>Exon</hi> Coll. <hi>Oxon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Diſcourſe of the Repugnancy of Sin to the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of Univerſal Reaſon; being a Diſwaſive from a Sinful Life, from Principles of common Wiſdom, currant amongſt all Man-kind, ſave in the Concerns of their Souls.</p>
            <p>A Diſcorſe proving from Scripture and Reaſon, that the Life of Man is not limited by any abſolute Decree of God, by the Author of the Duty of Man, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>The Importance of Religion to young Perſons repreſented in a Sermon Preached at the Funeral of Sir <hi>Thomas Viner,</hi> Baronet in St. <hi>Hellens</hi> Church <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, May</hi> the 3, 1683.</p>
            <p>A Private Peace-offering for the Diſcovery and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>appointment of the late horrid Conſpiracy againſt the King, &amp;c. In a Sermon Preached <hi>July</hi> the 8, 1683.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:63795:35"/>A Sermon Preached before the Lord Major and Court of Aldermen at the Church of St. <hi>Mary le Bow, Sep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tember</hi> the 9, 1683.</p>
            <p>All 3 by <hi>H. Heſketh,</hi> Miniſter of St. <hi>Hellens London,</hi> and Chaplain to his Majeſty.</p>
            <p>Providence bringing Good out of Evil, in a Sermon Preached the 9 of <hi>September,</hi> 1683. By <hi>Richard Pearſon</hi> Rector of St. <hi>Michaels Crooked-Lane.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
